<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full enquiry into the power of faith, the nature of prophecy, the translation of Enoch and Elias, and the resurrection of Christ</title>
            <author>Freke, William, 1662-1744.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12685735</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12685735</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 354:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full enquiry into the power of faith, the nature of prophecy, the translation of Enoch and Elias, and the resurrection of Christ</title>
                  <author>Freke, William, 1662-1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Freke. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Resurrection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FULL ENQUIRY INTO THE Power of Faith, THE <hi>Nature of Prophery,</hi> The Tranſlation of <hi>ENOCH</hi> and <hi>ELIAS,</hi> AND THE Reſurrection of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the YEAR 1693.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THIS Tract, however peculiar it may ſeem to Chriſtians, yet as is ſhewn hereafter, is not intended to exclude its ſelf from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Encouragement even of <hi>Jews, Mahumetans,</hi> and all other Profeſſions alſo: The Author endeavours to open wide to all the Common way to GOD, and 'tis one end of his Writing to demonſtrate that the Righteous of all Religions are accepted, and while they are ſincere, have equally Right to be the Heirs of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe therefore the Wiſdom of GOD, to cut off all manner of proud Cavils, for a Prerogative and Monopoly of Salvation, as he obſerves, ſeems purpoſely to have given us three ſeveral Examples of Tranſlation: The First in <hi>Enoch,</hi> to convince us of our acceptance in our Natural Light. The Second in <hi>Elijah,</hi> to ſhew you that for all their Law of Ceremonies, yet the <hi>Jews</hi> are not therefore rendred uncapable of ſo great a Bleſſing. And the laſt of Chriſt on his Reſurrection, to confirm his more profitable Precepts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I ſay, theſe three great Prophets ſignally in their Order exempliſie to us what Religion will be acceptable to GOD in us; and methinks their followers when they conſider it, need not be at ſuch variances as they are; for in truth how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diverſified by Circumſtances, yet in the main ſurely 'twas the ſame Faith that lead and directed each at the bottom; and the ſame Purity and Piety that drew down ſo ſingular a Reward and Teſtimony from GOD, to declare his Approbation of it.</p>
            <p>Nor would I have any Man therefore here offended that I ſignalize theſe great Prophets thus, for it is not as with a deſign to diminiſh or eclipſe the reſt from their real Value, but as the more bright the Example, the clearer Pattern have we to follow; ſo in the Holy Ambition of our ſeeking to GOD, ſurely we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not better fix our ſelves to imitate any than thoſe whom GOD has given ſuch his cleareſt declarations that he has moſt approved of.</p>
            <p>And thus could <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or any others therefore teach me this Heavenly Road, I would equally follow them as Chriſt my Redeemer, for would they not all go the ſame way? And yet on the other ſide, ſhall I leave his Directions who perfected himſelf before me the Journey of Faith he adviſes me unto, to follow that Man in the Road, that never travelled throughout in it himſelf?</p>
            <p>And in truth what ſays Christ himſelf otherwiſe to us in this matter? Does not he tell us, that 'twill be in vain for us to ſay, we have cryed, Lord, Lord, or done Miracles, in that great day, without we have lived well, and a life of Faith alſo: I will not ſay, that any man can heartily make his approaches unto GOD, and refuſe Chriſtianity, and on that account be ſaved without believing Chriſt, or elſe ſurely the way by Chriſt or otherwiſe were all one.</p>
            <p>Nor let any Man cenſure me in this neither, that I prefer <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> before either <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Apoſtles, to us indeed the latter excelled; <hi>Moſes</hi> as he was a Law-giver, and the Apoſtles as they delivered us down the Goſpel of Chriſt; but in the real efficacy of Faith, certainly <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended. GOD employs his Prophets in Meſſages, and makes them Illuſtrious to the World, according as his Mercies to Mankind incline him; but that they Triumph in Faith is through their Piety, and their own Application.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:4"/>
            <p>Thus what was it preſerved <hi>Noah,</hi> and made <hi>Abraham</hi> dear to GOD, was it not Faith? So, what was it that preſerved <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions Den, was it not Faith? I may ſay, are we ſo ridiculouſly Blaſphemous, as even contrary to the words of Scripture, and thoſe expreſs Directions there, that tell us that the immutable GOD is no reſpecter of Perſons, as to think that GOD took a fancy either to <hi>Noah, Abraham,</hi> or <hi>Daniel,</hi> as Men fondly practice; and if he did, why did the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> then prefer <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> before <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and why were they not all tranſlated, had not their weaker Faiths fallen far ſhort either of <hi>Enoch</hi>'s or <hi>Elijah</hi>'s?</p>
            <p>And for ſhame therefore let us lay by all theſe our Youthful Apprehenſions, and our petty Imaginations of Piety, which were good in their way, but now in the full light of Religion are but as Shadows to the more real Exerciſes of Faith: Were <hi>Enoch, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> nay, and Chriſt and <hi>Mahomet</hi> all true Prophets, and think you were they all preſent with us, they would not thus exhort us to a ſteady and firm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in our adoring GOD through Faith, and ſeeking his Kingdom. Alas! we all vainly Cavil about the out-ſide and ſhell of Religion, like the <hi>Jews,</hi> who valued themſelves upon Rites and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, though even their own Prophets reproved their Vanity in them in reſpect of the real Purity of the Heart, and while we let the Devil rob us of what ought to be even infinitely more dear to us.</p>
            <p>After all, I know nothing to be objected in this matter, but that I lay the value of Chriſtianity low; but alas, wherein? Chriſt came to teach us the way to GOD, and not to ſave us juſt in believing in his Name. And as for his great Leſſon of Inſtruction, this is it, 'twas Faith; and I endeavour to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend no other; you ſay, he tells us, That he that believes not in him is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and 'tis true enough, and I believe the Sentence irrevocable, where Men believe not on conviction. But doth not both Chriſt and his Apoſtles inform you, that the invincibly ignorant and the weak are excuſed in their Blindneſs? Nay, and that they ſhall be accepted in the way they can walk, <hi>John 9.41. James 4.17. Rom. 2.14, 15. John 15.22.24.</hi> And yet will we condemn them?</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, what I have wrote has been neither to abuſe the Scriptures, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate in Doctrines, or to injure our preſent Churches or Chriſtianity; if it has any tendency, 'tis but to explain a Doctrine long ſince delivered: Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> in his Treatiſe of Holy Dying, <hi>Cap. 3. Sect. 1. p. 59.</hi> is amply expreſs of the ſame mind; he tells you plainly how the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity not only remov'd their Immortality and Tranſlation by Death, but dwindled our Ages in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, firſt, from near <hi>1000</hi> to <hi>500</hi> years, and thence after to <hi>2</hi> and <hi>300,</hi> till it reſted at <hi>70,</hi> our preſent Period. Pray God for the future we prove as ready to reverſe this Curſe, as our fore-fathers were to fall in it.</p>
            <p>So, what ſays <hi>Luther</hi> to the ſame effect? Does he not tell us in his Table-Talk, <hi>p. 477.</hi> that <hi>Adam</hi> was Originally deſigned to be tranſlated? And ſo other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in many places, that if he had Faith, he did not doubt but that he could do any thing. But why ſhould I inſiſt longer on multiplying Humane Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for what I hope ere this Treatiſe be ended, to ſhew as conſiderable from Scripture, as for any Doctrine in Chriſtianity.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65762:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A FULL ENQUIRY INTO THE Power of Faith, the Nature of Prophecy, the Tranſlation of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> and the Reſurrection of Chriſt.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Kingdom of God in general.</head>
               <p>WHEN Chriſt entred upon his Office of Preaching the Goſpel, his firſt Leſſon was, <hi>Repent, for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is at hand,</hi> Mat. 4.17. So when he ſent out his Apoſtles, his charge to them was, after they had healed the Sick, to tell them, <hi>That the Kingdom of GOD was come nigh them,</hi> Luke 10.9. as if he would purpoſely inſinuate ſomething extraordinary approaching them beſides his Doctrine and their freedom from their Diſeaſes, upon his converſing with them, inſtructing and healing them.</p>
               <p>I have taken the freedom therefore in this caſe to examine by the reſt of the Scriptures what might be the meaning of ſo weighty an Expreſſion: I hope I ſhall not err by running into an Enthuſiaſtick Method in it; for I have reſolv'd never to let my Faith run counter to my Reaſon, or over-reach it; and on the other ſide, if in the ſearch of the Matter conſiderable and deep matters of Faith appear, not hitherto ſufficiently regarded, I hope a modeſt Recommendation of the ſame will offend no Man.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65762:5"/>
               <p>To explain therefore to thee the ſcope of what I have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and what thou mayeſt expect from me upon this Subject, I ſhall tell thee firſt what my apprehenſion of the words is, and after that deſcending more particularly into the ſeveral parts and branches of my Diſcourſe upon it; I ſhall endeavour both to anſwer from Scripture and Reaſon all manner of Objections and Difficulties that may be raiſed againſt my ſenſe of them.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt thing, thou wilt find I have laid it down from hence as a certain Rule, that all Men, I mean of all Religions and Perſwaſions whatever, have the means in their hands, if they improve them, of reaching to and attaining this <hi>Kingdom of GOD,</hi> not only of the lower meaſures of Grace I mean, but the higheſt pitches of Glory; that is, not only of the common aſſiſtances of the Spirit, but of Prophecy and Miracles, nay, and even of Tranſlation alſo; and this I apprehend was that great Doctrine of the Kingdom that Chriſt came to inſtruct us in, and that was the full and true ſcope both of thoſe his words and the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And this is that Kingdom, which, if I miſtake not, he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in that his moſt excellent Form of Prayer, ſaying, <hi>Thy Kingdom come;</hi> this is that Kingdom wherein the Millenariſts expect Chriſt's Reign on the Earth, and this is that Kingdom whereby Chriſt will deſtroy Antichriſt with the very Glory of his Coming; in truth this is that Kingdom that the Apoſtle makes the very Crown and Perfection of our Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5.</p>
               <p>And though there ſeems a poſſibility that with <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> we might attain this Kingdom without ſuch the Inſtruction of Chriſt: Yet ſince GOD has added a further help to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and our Natural Light through him that was to be a Sacrifice for the World, ſhall we contemptuouſly ſet aſide this newer Light, that has added the moſt lively Inſtructions as well as his Example to this bare Poſſibility and Idea of the Kingdom of GOD only?</p>
               <p>Nor need it diſcourage us in this caſe that the Apoſtles of Chriſt wrote not much of this Doctrine, unleſs in repeating his words, as it was what neither they nor the World could then bear; juſt as <hi>Elijah</hi> knew nothing of his Tranſlation till the day came, though he were a Prophet before, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.4. and as the Spirit reveals it ſelf altogether to our occaſions; but now in the latter Ages of the World what hinders but that GOD may reveal it more manifeſtly in comfort to his Church, and to draw
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65762:5"/>the Reformiſts or his new <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the Bonds of Spiritual <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> or Popery, and to unite and draw into one Fold all the Elect in the ſeveral Churches of the World when the Fulneſs of Time is come, can we think GOD will want proper means to execute his Will, when we ſee rather than fail, that he could make even a wicked High-Prieſt to Prophecy, that 'twas neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that Chriſt ſhould dye for the People.</p>
               <p>If therefore by this little Eſſay I ſhall be able to ſhew this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine not only conſonant to the higheſt Reaſon, but, the moſt genuine Scripture, I mean of the Old as well as New Teſtament, I hope no one will condemn me only for illuſtrating and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Rays of ſo great a truth; nor be afraid therefore, Reader, to receive freely what I write in it, I pretend to nothing but a plain and ſincere Reaſoning and Expoſition of Scripture by it, and I hope no way tending to beguile thee.</p>
               <p>But if on the other ſide, the ſtate of our Faith be really ſuch as I have repreſented it to thee, I know not why we ſhould any longer ſlight ſo great a truth; ſhould we not rather couragiouſly reflect that we have a better Country, as I have propoſed thee? Here we are lyable to Wrongs, Wounds, and all manner of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents; and had we not better then ſeek for the Spiritual <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and Pray to enter the Kingdom of GOD, where neither Vipers will be able to hurt us, Lions devour us, nor Fiery Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces conſume us; where the Sun will be forced to ſtand ſtill, and Mountains to move at our Commands, and whether Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threaten the World either by Fire or Water, yet at leaſt like <hi>Noah, Jonas,</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> we ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p>I know at preſent to believe the truth of this Doctrine is to ſeem contumeliouſly to accuſe the World of Corruption, and a Man muſt expect a Cenſure and Treatment for it accordingly; and yet methinks for all theſe difficulties I cannot for my part but believe it, it ſeems ſo entirely agreeable to Scripture and Reaſon, that I could as ſoon not be a Chriſtian, as not aſſent to it: And as for the Corruption of the World, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> could ſay of his Times, <hi>There is none righteous, no, not one,</hi> Rom. 3.10. it may be no difficulty to ſay ſo now, for ſurely there were as ood Men in the Apoſtles Age as ours.</p>
               <p>But alas, what good will Apologies do one in this matter? We that have ſuch an Infidel Generation amongſt us, that 'tis even ridiculous to talk or write of either a Spiritual Kingdom or Faith amongſt them; can one expect that either Senſe or Reaſon can
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65762:6"/>convince them, or reconcile them to an Hypotheſis of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the Reſurrection of the Dead at leaſt muſt and can be the only real Foundation either of Chriſtianity, or any other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for what would Precepts avail without their Reward? I hope to God that even that does not paſs to ſlighty by way of Figure and Allegory amongſt us alſo.</p>
               <p>Nor ſhall I wonder in this caſe that Men endeavour to ſtifle this Kingdom neither; is not this that Kingdom that Satan has endeavoured all along to deſtroy, that he reduc'd unto <hi>Noah</hi> in the Flood, and that he has raiſed up Antichriſt to confound? Indeed, is not this that Kingdom that he has clouded and ſealed up all along from the Wiſe of this World, and to which, as the Apoſtle obſerves, <hi>not many wiſe, not many mighty, nor many noble are called,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26. And yet through which we have an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance that he will pour out his Spirit in the latter days.</p>
               <p>Surely therefore I may add, if ever we intend to make any Progreſs in Chriſtianity, in this Kingdom it is that we muſt lay our Foundation, and which, as I may ſay, perfectly harmonizes with the Revelations both of <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt. I am not Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, however I ſhall add a Modern Prophecy alſo about it, 'tis ſaid to be <hi>Withers</hi>'s, and 'tis not unlikely; for he not only wrote a Comment upon the Lord's Prayer to the ſame effect, but really his Writings ſhew him a Man of ſo admirable a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Piety, that he ſeemed a proper Object for ſo great a Gift: But be it whoſe you will, the words are as follows.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Kingdom which the Jew did long ago</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mould out according to his erring Brain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And whereof many Zealous Chriſtians too</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Unwarrantable Fancies entertain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Kingdom whereof now in Types we hear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall to the World eſſentially appear.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Now if GOD therefore has ſet us thus to be tryed on the Stage of this World according as we make our Attainments to this Glorious Kingdom, had we not better then with an Holy Ambition let him Glory in us as Conquerors, than become the deſpicable Captives of the Devil? Not I mean, that we ſhould be lofty or proud with this Ambition neither; for if ever we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to Conquer, it muſt be by an entire and Lamb-like Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Will of GOD.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65762:6"/>
               <p>To be ſhort, this is that Kingdom that we are told is within us, and that <hi>comes not by Obſervation,</hi> Luke 17.20, 21. and for which we need not to go to the Wilderneſs of Teachers, that cry, lo here Chriſt, and lo there, for 'tis in our Hearts, and whence if we hold faſt that which is good, and quench not the Spirit, but permit him to lead us through an entire reſignation into all his Paths of Holy Suggeſtions, we muſt needs attain it: And whereas on the contrary, in the Kingdom of Satan, and where our Sins bear Rule, St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.13. That our Luſts will bring forth Sin, and that the Wages of Sin are Death.</p>
               <p>But that I may the better proceed on this Subject, I ſhall here ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">Of the Criſis of our Tryal in general.</note> that there are two diſtinct great Kingdoms; to wit, the firſt of GOD, and the latter of Satan; as alſo that they have their ſeveral and diſtinct Criſis's and meaſures of Judgment: But firſt, a little of this matter in general.</p>
               <p>Alas! who that's either Chriſtian, Jew, or Turk, or that but believes the Old Teſtament, can forbear lamenting to ſee the Devil's Tyranny through ſin in <hi>Adam,</hi> poor, dying, deformed, and wretched Man; a Creation groaning, and longing to be delivered, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.22. What are our Riches, Coaches, and ſine Cloaths, but as Rags to our Innocence loſt? Will they avail us any thing either againſt Death, or Sorrow; or are they able to keep us from the Dreadful Day at laſt?</p>
               <p>And yet for all this, and though that if we Repent, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is at hand; nay, and though we have a Promiſe, that if we firſt ſeek the Kingdom of GOD, all other things ſhall be added unto it; as if GOD had expreſly reverſed the Curſe of the Earth, and reſolved rather than fail, with the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> to feed us with Manna and Quails on our firſt ſtep of retreat towards the Heavenly Paradiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. Yet alas, who ſeeks to GOD, either for Eternal Life or Neceſſaries, as they ſhould do?</p>
               <p>No, we are all run aſtray, ſome one way, ſome another; ſome are drowned in Infidelity, and neither regard what either Scripture or Reaſon informs them; others are perfectly, ſtupidly negligent, and regard no more what yet they cannot but believe, than a fair Story that they have heard with delight. And yet the Spirit of God warns us all, and ſo leaves all inexcuſable to their Condemnation.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65762:7"/>
               <p>And hence alſo it is that every Man whatever has his hour of Viſitation, and which will and muſt certainly continue to lead him right, and that even to perfection, if he follow and not reſiſt it. And hence every Man I ſee methinks ſhews me an Angel or a Devil, in making ſome moving on to one degree of Perfection, and others to another, while others ſtarting aſide like a broken Bow, and uneaſie to follow the leading of GOD's Spirit, proudly ſeek Devices of their own, and ſo are loſt in their own Contrivances.</p>
               <p>So hence 'tis that others making their application imperfectly to GOD are forced to be purged for it through Martyrdom or Death, when could they learn with <hi>Enoch</hi> but to walk perfectly with GOD, canſt thou think, Friend, that he would let them dye? No, know GOD is no reſpecter of Perſons, the whole courſe of Scriptures, beſides general Texts, witneſs it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.35. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</p>
               <p>And yet beware how thou raſhly attempt this, for know theſe Glories are defended by a fiery Tryal, and before thou attaineſt them thou wilt find a real Fight of Infidelity, Pride, and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and a terrible one too; thy little ſeekings of Curioſity and Paſſion will not avail for this Kingdom, no, 'tis worthy of thy Conſtancy; and therefore ſuch Luſts thou mayſt be ſure will but obſtruct thy proceedings.</p>
               <p>Take care therefore and purifie thy Heart throughly; for know as thy great Conflicts will be between GOD and thy ſelf in private, where no body ſees, and where you will be forced to fight your way through Principalities and Mights to the Kingdom of GOD, and wreſtle with the Powers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. So you muſt expect to be moſt exactly pure, for that alone can ſupport you, and which if you are, you need not fear any dangers; nay, rather thou mayeſt joy againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, when he brings his Temptations to deſtroy thy Hopes, for if thou thus truſt in GOD, they muſt advance them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay then, if Chriſt for theſe Reaſons, has aſſured us that the Kingdom of Heaven has through his Inſtructions and Example ſuffered Violence,<note place="margin">Exhortation.</note> and may be taken by force? Nay, if he himſelf has gone the way before us, why ſhould we longer obſtruct ſo great a Grace, by delighting to welter in our Iniquities? Perverſe Man, that will not skill his Seaſons of Grace; Man, more ſottiſh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65762:7"/>than Birds or Beaſts; they know their Times and Seaſons, and follow the Inſtincts of their Nature, but Man will not follow the leadings of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>We dare not truſt the words of Chriſt our Saviour; like <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> we will not neglect our Temporal Affairs, though but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, to get the one and great thing neceſſary, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42. much leſs ſell all, to purchaſe the Field where we find the Precious Stone of Life hid: We dare not venture to loſe our Lives for Chriſt's ſake, and the Goſpel's, though if we do, he has promiſed us, that inſtead of it we ſhall find them, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.24.</p>
               <p>Nor is this a work of Learning to baulk Men neither, indeed Sincerity is all in all in it, and 'tis offered to all alike; in truth the Kingdom of GOD is within us, and our Thoughts muſt Conduct us right towards it if we are but exactly ſincere: And hence alſo, as <hi>Withers</hi> excellently ſays, the true and only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to Prophecy is but to retire alone, read the Scriptures, and contemplate; and 'tis only our Corruptions that hinder us, or elſe I might add, our own very Hearts would lead us right.</p>
               <p>'Tis true indeed, we ought not to ſlight any further help that is offered us, eſpecially if it come from GOD, but elſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion alone were enough: We ſee Chriſt was poor, and I believe <hi>Enoch</hi> had very few or no Books, and yet they both at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it; alas! we would perſwade our ſelves that it is harder than it is, and when indeed GOD in Juſtice makes the offers of his Salvation to all in common, and not to the Rich and Learned only; if he had, Chriſt had never given them ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Woes as he did.</p>
               <p>Come then, my Brethren, I mean of all Religions, eat of that Bread of Chriſt, more excellent than Manna, and that will not let you dye, <hi>John</hi> 6.49, 50.58. and drink of his Fountain of Living Waters, <hi>John</hi> 4.14. Venture to purchaſe that Field, where his great Treaſure lyes, and beg of his Leaven to purifie your Hearts; be not ſo unjuſt as to charge all the Follies of Men as Imperfections in Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Nor be afraid of the Hardſhips of ſingular Truth, Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf is no ſuffering Religion; 'tis Sin only draws down our Afflictions, or elſe Chriſtianity would make us Immortal: What therefore though GOD hide his Face from thee for a time, yet he is ſtill near thee, and cannot forſake thee. So, what though a <hi>Shimei</hi> mock thee by chance, bear it but as from GOD, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65762:8"/>as there is no Accident before him, ſo thy Faith thus in every Croſs and Curſe thou haſt will but haſten thy Tryal.</p>
               <p>And ſo, what though thou wilt ſcarce perceive when thou enterſt this happy and invincible Stage of Faith, yet deſpair not; and if thou be but found doing good, thou needeſt not fear it, though Chriſt come as a Thief in the Night; nor be diſmayed at delays, for though GOD will try thee firſt, e're he confirm thee in it, by Dream or Viſion; yet if thou prayeſt and liveſt exactly, thou art not ſurer even that thou art, than that thou art entred, and if thou humbly perſevere, thou wilt, nay, muſt Conquer.</p>
               <p>What, have we not near an Hundred times in Scripture Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that if we ask and ſeek, it ſhall be given us? And ſhall we only deſpair at and refrain ſeeking the Kingdom of GOD? And that we are principally commanded to ask.</p>
               <p>Nor is our Evil Criſis in this caſe leſs certain than our good;<note place="margin">Of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Criſis.</note> for as it were to Blaſpheme God's Juſtice, to ſay, that St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converſion which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he erred in his Zeal ignorantly, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. and <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi>'s Viſion was accidental, or <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Burial by GOD himſelf, or Chriſt's Reſurrection at three days by chance; ſo were it not leſs a guilt to ſay, that even the Puniſhment of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah,</hi> the Flood, the <hi>Canaanites, Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> were Arbitrary, and without exact Juſtice. What, ſhall Chriſt tell us, that GOD has a care even of the very hairs of our Heads, and of Sparrows, and can we ſuppoſe him Juſt, and yet wanton in ſuch a Deſtruction of Man? Nay, indeed do not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures aſſure us, that he waited till their Iniquities were at the full?</p>
               <p>So undoubtedly alſo there is a ſet Bound of Corruption, even to Witcheraft; and though till ſuch as <hi>Job</hi>'s and <hi>Saul</hi>'s Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we are ſeldom at the bent of ſuch Tryals as to conſult Witches, and to curſe GOD to live; yet remember that when ſuch Tryals come, even the beſt ſhall not be ſpared if they fall; for as even <hi>Lucifer</hi> fell, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſhut out of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> for his ſin, ſo if thou fling not thy ſelf wholly upon GOD in theſe Tryals, thou wilt aſſuredly miſcarry, whether thou forbear in Pride or heedleſneſs, 'tis all one, there is a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too ſubtle for thee; and whereas if thou relyeſt on GOD, thou canſt not poſſibly be too weak for his Grace.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65762:8"/>
               <p>And the better to keep thee from this Preſumption, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber therefore that even Chriſt himſelf, the Son of GOD incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, was forced to learn this Obedience, and ſeek to him with ſtrong crying and tears for his Kingdom, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. And yet be not diſmayed thereat, for for all that, thou muſt certainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come if thou walkeſt but upright; nor fear if thou truſt in GOD, he will not let thee be carried away with the Wiles of Satan; no, he will ſecure thee ſo, that no catch ofa Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be able to ſurprize thee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7, 8. — 12.9. But then, as GOD told the Jews, 'tis not for your deſerts, but from himſelf alone that he bleſſes you: So that after all, we muſt learn from Chriſt to ſay, that we are unproſitable Servants, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his Goodneſs only.</p>
               <p>By this time I hope therefore that you believe that neither Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">God's Imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality.</note> nor the Prophets were favoured in their Tryals; indeed that they had ſeveral Commiſſions was as the Wiſdom of GOD directed, but that they became Prophets was, that they improved that Grace of GOD that is offered to all Mankind in common; and hence 'tis that we are told, that Chriſt himſelf was exalted for his Righteouſneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.9. and was to grow in Wiſdom, and through bitter Temptations to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Kingdom of GOD: And hence alſo the Apoſtles, who had a peculiar advance in Faith through Chriſt's Inſtructions, yet after all were forced to attain it through Watching and Purity.</p>
               <p>And hence it was, that after <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt had opened the Kingdom of Heaven through Faith, many others took courage, became Prophets, and followed them: Whereas after a dead Infidelity has once invaded the World, it has required the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar care of Providence to renew our Faith again; for though by chance GOD in Mercy may have given Viſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations even to Children and impure Perſons, for the ſake of others, and as indeed he did once by an Aſſe, yet a full and perfect ſource of Prophecy is only attainable through a real Purity.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay,<note place="margin">Objections to it.</note> did not GOD particularly favour the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whilſt he curſed <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan?</hi> No, as to Temporalities poſſibly he might, but as to the main current of his Juſtice 'twas as ſincere to the one as the other: Thus he would not expel the <hi>Canaanites</hi> till their Iniquities were grown to the full, and <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65762:9"/>had not been deſtroyed, had there been but five Righteous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons remaining therein; and even the Old World had the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of GOD for 120 Years ere they were deſtroyed by the Flood.</p>
               <p>I ſee the matter, we would fain excuſe our Luſts, and fling all on GOD, we would fain make his ways unequal, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did about the ſour Grapes, when they aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed GOD, that the ſins of the Fathers ſet the Childrens Teeth on edge. But what, are not theſe Calumnies falſe, and have we not reaſon on the contrary to be even raviſhed with the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Love of GOD?</p>
               <p>But to illuſtrate this the better, ſhall not GOD beſtow one or five Talents on whom he pleaſes? Shall the Stone complain that he is not a Plant, and the Horſe, that he is not a Man, or the Man, that he is not an Angel? Or what, ought we not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all to joyn together to be thankful for the Bounty of our Maker? At this rate, like <hi>Lucifer</hi> elſe, we ſhall endeavour at laſt to be our own Carvers even of the God-head alſo.</p>
               <p>I ſay then, if GOD gives him that has one Talent a fair Tryal as well as him that has two, or him that has two, a fair Tryal as well as him that has five, have they reaſon to complain? no ſurely. Nor is this our caſe neither, for GOD is more good than ſo; he has promiſed to increaſe our Talents likewiſe if we uſe them well, and if ſo, where is the leaſt room for thoſe Calumnies? Have we not rather reaſon to admire the infinite, and unfathomable Mercies and Judgments of GOD?</p>
               <p>Nor is the Objection from the Parable of the Labourers of any obſtruction or difficulty in this matter neither, for what though as our Saviour therein tells us, that he that comes in to work at the latter end of the day, ſhall have his Peny equally with him that bore the heat of the day; muſt that deſtroy the degrees of Glory, which his Apoſtles alſo have revealed unto us, and which he himſelf alſo has declared by his Parable of the Talents? No, rather every Man ſhall anſwer for his Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, and live longer or ſhorter, or work more or leſs, yet ſhall no ſuch accidental Advantages benefit or injure him, but only his true and real advance through the Grace of God.</p>
               <p>But you ſay, GOD protected <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt from their Infancy; and why not? Where he has ſown an extraordinary Seed of many Talents for the good of the World and his own Glory, may not he juſtly in ſuch a caſe alſo give notice of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65762:9"/>birth of ſuch a Seed; nay, and give it an extraordinary Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and that without the leaſt prejudice to his Juſtice in their Tryals?</p>
               <p>Thus could St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s peculiar Call keep him from working out his Salvation with fear and trembling, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and keeping his Body under, leſt whilſt he Preached, he himſelf ſhould be caſt away, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. Thus, could <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Height ſecure him, or <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Revelations bring him into the Land of <hi>Canaan?</hi> Or to put the Argument to a higher Topick, will you queſtion that Juſtice that even the Devil does not, who upon his certainty of its ſincerity ventured to tempt even our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus? No, no, the ways of God are too immutable to be drawn aſide at any time into petty ſhifts and by-ways.</p>
               <p>Nor on the ſame Account may we ſafely venture to Judge any Man; what, do we not ſee that greateſt Sinners every day Repent? And does not the Spirit often chooſe unlikely means to Worldly appearance, leſt therefore like thoſe who would not let even that great Prophet Chriſt Jeſus have Honour in his own Country; let us forbear to cenſure and judge the Mercies and Judgments of God, which are unfathomable: Let us not look therefore on what Men are, or have been, but what they may be.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole matter therefore, if God uſually lets the Father's Ignorances deſcend on the Son, according to his Fourth Commandment, and as we feel to our ſorrow through the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and his Piety come as a Bleſſing to increaſe the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of his Generation, as he did in <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet if he allows them equally fair Tryals, is he not Juſt? And if he gives him that has one Talent five for the Improvement, or takes his away quite that abuſes them, is not this Juſt alſo? O the wonders of the Mercies and Judgments of GOD! who can ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Mercies, or dread the terrible Juſtice of our God?</p>
               <p>And yet though the Scriptures,<note place="margin">Of our gradual acceſs herein.</note> in purſuance of this Doctrine, acquaints us, that we ſhall not all dye, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. as if the wickedneſs of one part of the World ſhould draw down immediate Judgment; and of the other ſide, its Purity ſhould attract Tranſlation at the Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all things: Yet for all this we may aſſure our ſelves, that this Conqueſt muſt be by a Gradual Acceſs. Chriſt tells us, that the Kingdom of GOD is like a Seed ſown, that ſprings up we know not how.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65762:10"/>
               <p>Ue muſt not expect therefore to jump out of one ſtate into another, whether into Miracles or Tranſlation, but to proceed by degrees, and as our time of Tryal will lead us; for as <hi>Nemo repente fit turpiſſimus,</hi> ſo <hi>Nemo repente fit optimus</hi> is as true; and as if there were an Hundred Journeys to the Kingdom of GOD, ſo we muſt have an Hundred riſes and Stonds in Prayer and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ere we can receive our Crown.</p>
               <p>We may ſee at firſt that <hi>Adam</hi> was intended for a tryal of time, as he was to be Fruitful and multiply ere he was to be tranſlated; and if he, as made a Prophet, was in a ſtate of delay, what muſt we expect then that are a compleat Stage below him, and that require as long a time ere we can be Prophets alſo? Surely, I ſay, we may well have Patience; would we travel our two long Journeys in a Minute, or perfect ſuch a Stage in an Hour?</p>
               <p>And thus, ſuppoſe our ſtate to Prophecy required Ten Years the perfecteſt application to GOD, and in the abſoluteſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation after we are adult, and as indeed ſeems rational enough in the Age of Chriſt; and ſo I ſay, ſuppoſe the like time were allotted for our Stage of Tranſlation alſo, could we be ſo unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable as to be angry at this Bound of Tryal ſet us by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Or ſhould we not rather patiently wait the leiſure and Laws of our Puriſication in it?</p>
               <p>Had we not as rationally expect an Infant to be a Man, and an Acron to be an Oak in a day, and ſo over-rule all the Laws of Heaven? Surely we had: And if ſo, why may not we have the Natural Patience of all things? Nay, and ſince we ſee that even the very World its ſelf is forced to grow old, and purifie it ſelf thus by degrees.</p>
               <p>But what, after all doſt thou think that thy Tryal propoſed is tedious and difficult, and that the many miſcarriages of others quite diſcourages all thy Endeavours towards it? Alas! thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteſt that Gold is not Gold till 'tis tryed in the Furnace; and our Sovereign Maker in all the Juſtice of the World has reaſon to take us for no other than tinſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſs for all our gawdy and gilded appearance of Uprightneſs, until we have ſtood a due ſhock of Tryals and Temptations; and after all, who ſhall ſay to God, that Juſtice is not an Attribute worthy of the goodneſs of the Divine Majeſty?</p>
               <p>Beſides God is more good than to leave our gain ſo deſperate too, he has reſerved many leſſer Meaſures, and leſſer Crowns,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65762:10"/>and degrees of Glory for them who with hearty endeavours fail of attaining the higheſt. And what then, though thou art not one of thoſe ones of Myriads that have attained Tranſlation, or thoſe ones of Millions that have attained to be Prophets; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> could rather deſire to be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of God, than a Prince in the Tents of Wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>So further, remember that if thou doſt ſet about this great Work, that thou do it not like the Sons <hi>of Zebedee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Humility.</note> by ſeeking the chief place only, leave that Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to GOD, and if thou doſt ſo, and doſt well, 'tis impoſſible but that by degrees he muſt give it thee: Nor be grieved that GOD does not immediately appear to thee by Viſion or Revelation; remember 'tis in Mercy, that he will not lead us further than we are perfect, leſt we be deſtroyed: The Offences that in the Vale of Ignorance are light and trivial a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the full Glory of GOD's Revelations and Commands, magnifie like <hi>Achan</hi>'s, <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi>'s, and <hi>Abiram</hi>'s. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, and that if we there fall away, we muſt never expect to be renewed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p>Take care therefore, for as at beſt GOD will fruſtrate all ſuch Superſtitious Expectations of Faith, ſo if thou haſt no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bottom than ſuch Stubble and Straw of Curioſity to truſt to, thou muſt expect that when GOD's purifying Fire comes, that though thou art raiſed even as high as <hi>Lucifer</hi> in thy conceit, yet all will conſume and fall, yea, and thou with it; nay, and that though thou raiſe thy <hi>Babel</hi> a Thouſand times, if it does not do worſe, and run thee into Enthuſiaſm and the Deluſions of Satan.</p>
               <p>And yet for all this thou muſt ſtill work it out with Patience; thou muſt not think now only to aim at a Tabernacle here, and with the Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Patriarchs reſt at a Pilgrimage in this World only; for though <hi>David</hi> and others were Men in their time, and Light after GOD's own Heart, yet now we have a more perfect and holy Example, to wit, Chriſt Jeſus, a Prieſt after the Order of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> that never dyes, and greater than <hi>Abraham, Heb.</hi> 7.3. So that now we are without Excuſe, if that we only ſeek an Earthly <hi>Canaan;</hi> for to what end does Light come into the World, if we ſtill remain in Darkneſs?</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, the Apoſtles attained not hereto, and yet were very Holy Men; and what then? Do they not all confeſs themſelves the imperfect followers of the great Pattern Chriſt Jeſus? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> I might judge that it was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65762:11"/>their Contentions and Propriety in Converſions that kept them from their growth in this Kingdom; but I forbear to cenſure, as I am ſure if I do, I cannot be certain, however by the effect 'tis plain that there was ſomething wanting in them, as there was in their caſting out ſome Devils, that they could not but by Faſting and Prayer, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.39, 40. But I leave their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to GOD.</p>
               <p>To proceed therefore, thou muſt not for all this let theirs, nor any others failings make thee forbear thy hopes for Purity and Happineſs; no, as I have ſaid, let GOD be true, and every Man a lyar: Nor fear, for if thou art exactly ſincere, thou muſt conquer; nor be diſmayed that thou haſt hitherto lived in ſin, for Chriſt has ſhewn thee by his Parable, that though thou come in at the latter end of the day, yet 'tis all one; indeed 'twill be thy pitch and continuance in Faith, that will be all in all.</p>
               <p>But thou art a <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Turk,</hi> and canſt not meet with Reaſon ſufficient to Convert thee to Chriſtianity: And what then? If thou followeſt it but in this alone, and art ſincere, and art not wilful in thine own Ignorances, 'tis impoſſible but that thou muſt Conquer; and rather than thou ſhalt fail, of a neceſſary truth, if thou perſevere in this courſe to ſeek the Kingdom of GOD, and conform to an exact Scrutiny of Truth, even GOD himſelf will reveal it to thee, as he did it to St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Acts Cap.</hi> 9, 10.</p>
               <p>Let us chearfully then ſet about this great Work, and try to Rival one another in it, and in who can help each other moſt towards it; let us Pray without ceaſing, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.16. and let us add to that a purifying Induſtry, that we may not tempt GOD; are we not Cowards to let <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> through the Law of Nature, and a Law of Ceremonies and Shadows enter this Kingdom, whilſt we are ſhut out, that not only have the Example, but the moſt particular Inſtructions of Chriſt to help us towards it?</p>
               <p>You Object, That the Tranſlation of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> was not on this Account, but rather with the Reſurrection of Chriſt, to give an Ocular Demonſtration to the ſeveral Ages of the World of the Immortality of the Soul. But why ſhould you furmiſe thus? Do the Scriptures ſay thus? Nay, do they not plainly ſay the contrary, and make all the meer effect of Faith? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5. If ſo, then let us no longer lye Idle, and be thus deceived with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65762:11"/>the appearance of Truth only, let us embrace the Scriptures throughly, or reject them wholly.</p>
               <p>But alas, in truth the thing is our Luſts are in our way, and we reſiſt the leading of GOD's Spirit, and ſo it is that he is forced to perfect us as high as he can; alas, we are ſo far from moving Mountains, and making Iron ſwim with our Faith, that with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> we ſink the firſt ſtep we take on the Water; we have not the Faith even to give us a Mortal <hi>Canaan,</hi> or to make the Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> fall; how ſhall we then expect the Spiritual <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> amongſt us?</p>
               <p>But as we can't 'tis our own fault, and only ours; we will not follow the Spirit of GOD, I am ſure that he tryes us e're he leaves us, and meerly the cunning of the Devil cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant us; is he nigh us? GOD is nearer, and thou canſt not fall but by thine own privity; but when inſtead of Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly following GOD's leading Methods to Wiſdom, through Meditation and Conſcience thou reſiſt them, do you think you do not ſtop up your own way?</p>
               <p>And from this wilful and perverſe Spirit of Infidelity it is that GOD has been forced, as I have ſaid, once in 2000 years or leſs, either to deſtroy the World, as he did by the Flood, or elſe in Mercy to raiſe up ſome new Patterns of Faith to lead us again; and thus he gave us <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt, after both whom ſome afreſh begun to ſerve GOD in Purity, and to become Prophets alſo; but alas, how ſoon are we returned, like the Dog, to his Vomit, and ſunk into our old Infidelity again?</p>
               <p>In truth one may juſtly ſay of the beſt of Men amongſt us now adays, they entertain ſo many Vertues, and ſo many Vices, ſo much Piety, and ſo much Sin, and which continually encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with one another in them; if Vice prevails, he is moſtly wicked, if Vertue, he is our good Man. O that we could but ſay of any of us, that Sin and Vice were quite extinct in us, at leaſt as to our will, if not to frailty! for then, with <hi>Enoch,</hi> might we be truly ſaid to walk with GOD alſo.</p>
               <p>But beſides this I may add, and what, ſhall we never learn, with the bleſſed <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Anna,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to wait with a doe Patience for the Kingdom of GOD, <hi>Mark</hi> 15.43. <hi>Luke</hi> 23.51. If with them we do not happen to riſe to the greateſt Perfection, yet at leaſt we ſhall find that GOD at laſt will accept us, and bleſs us for our hearty endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour's ſake as far as they reach, and ſurely that will be better than a dead Infidelity.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65762:12"/>
               <p>Come unto Chriſt, then, all ye that are weary, and heavy laden, for his Yoke is eaſie, and his Burthen is light; indeed you need fear nothing under his Conduct, as heavier Scholars indeed GOD pricks us forwards through Afflictions, but if we ſincerely endeavour to be perfect, he cannot but take them from us; for then even Angels will deliver us out of Priſon, Ravens will be forced to feed us, and the mouths of Lions will be ſtopt againſt us, only Chriſt ſuffered in this ſtate of Purity, and that for our ſakes, and by his own conſent; he not only tells us he could have more than Twelve Legions of Angels to help him, if he pleaſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.53. but even his Perſecutors were forced to go back and fall down from his Preſence, e're they could ſeize him, <hi>John</hi> 18.6.</p>
               <p>As the All-juſt GOD therefore cannot inflict the Puniſhment or Purgation on thoſe that walk as pure already, ſo let us learn to cheriſh this little Muſtard-ſeed of the Kingdom of GOD till it become as a Tree, and wherein all the Vertues of Divinity and Morality may flouriſh, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.32. <hi>Elijah</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Guards, <hi>Moſes</hi> drowned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt in the Red Sea; and we have a Promiſe even to bind Kings in Chains, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with Links of Iron: And think you not that theſe things were done, and theſe promiſes made for the Example, and the Encouragement of the Saints?</p>
               <p>'Tis true, St. <hi>Paul</hi> by his being wrap'd up into the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and St. <hi>John</hi> by his having the Revelations given him, ſeem only of the Apoſtles to have made their approaches near this Perfection; Transfigurations and ſuch Viſions being the uſual dawnings of Tranſlation, as Divine Dreams are of Prophecy: And they failed too, but what if they did, were they not Men as well as we? They had a greater meaſure of Chriſt's help and Example indeed, but what, is GOD a reſpecter of Perſons? And have we not the ſame offers of Grace, and as fair a Tryal given us, as ever they had?</p>
               <p>For ſhame therefore let us ſerve GOD with all our ſtrength, and all our might,<note place="margin">The Compleat Faith.</note> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 12.30. and ſo recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our ſelves more nearly to his Protection, and that can only be through a vigorous Faith. The Scriptures have told us already, that Faith without Works is dead; and I ſhall add alſo, that Works without Faith to lead them are dead alſo, I mean as to the Kingdom of GOD. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith 'tis impoſſible to ſee or pleaſe GOD, whereas our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65762:12"/>Faith, if it be ſtrong, it muſt prevail; nay, and though it be erring, if not wilfully, as appears by <hi>Cornelius</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Whereas on the contrary, if it be ſtrong and evil, it muſt needs draw down Enthuſiaſm and Deluſion upon us.</p>
               <p>And hence it is that our Saviour tells us, <hi>That all things are poſſible to him that believes,</hi> Mark 9.23. Indeed he ſays, <hi>Had we the Faith of a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, we might at a word remove this Sycamine-tree, or Mountain, and caſt it into the Sea,</hi> Luke 17.6. And hence it is that, <hi>O ye of little Faith,</hi> is almoſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Expoſtulatory upbraiding throughout the whole Goſpels, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.41.</p>
               <p>Hence likewiſe it is that his Apoſtles after him, when they had their Faith once ſtrengthned in themſelves to move it in others, tell us, <hi>That whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. So alſo that Faith was imputed to <hi>Abraham</hi> for Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.22. And therefore to uſe their Argument, though at the time of our Ignorance GOD winked at us, yet now he expects we ſhould Repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. and remain in our dead and brutiſh Infidelity no longer.</p>
               <p>Nay further, this Faith of the Kingdom of GOD is the only real and excellent Faith; to believe barely in Chriſt, and that he was crucified, is no more than what the Devils believe, and yet have ſtill reaſon to tremble; but to believe in him, and to act purſuant to his moſt excellent Doctrine of the Kingdom, and to lead good Lives, is to follow the deſign and ſcope of his Goſpel, and is that active Faith which only has the Promiſes of Salvation.</p>
               <p>But why do I remain on the brink of my Argument thus? Hath not Chriſt even expreſly promiſed, <hi>That thoſe that keep his ſayings, ſhall never ſee Death?</hi> John 8.51. And <hi>that thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, ſhall never dye,</hi> John 11.26. <hi>but are paſſed from death unto life,</hi> John 5.24. And doth he not expreſly limit this Death in his Diſcourſe to our Life in this World as well as the other? <hi>John</hi> 6.49, 50.58. Nay, has he not promiſed us more, that we ſhall do greater Works than he himſelf has done; and really whatever we ſhall ask in Faith, <hi>John</hi> 14.12.</p>
               <p>As Sin therefore is the Road to Death, as alſo Grace is to Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.21. So let us through theſe Encouragements of Chriſt learn to avoid our Sins and Luſts, which run us into Sin and Death, <hi>James</hi> 1.15. and follow thoſe ways that lead us to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65762:13"/>and Life. The Apoſtles that could not get out of Priſon themſelves, yet through the Prayers of the Church had their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, <hi>Acts</hi> 12. And can you think, that had they purified themſelves exactly, as Chriſt did, they would not have opened the Priſon Doors of themſelves, as well as <hi>Elijah</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Guards? Yes, undoubtedly they might, and God ſhewed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act meaſures of Juſtice in all theſe Events, or elſe 'twere imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, nay, impoſſible that theſe things ſhould be written for our Example and Encouragement; and what needed elſe that Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſo wonderfully magnified and exhorted to a Powerful Faith, as is done eſpecially, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. if the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts they left were only juſt deſigned for themſelves to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low?</p>
               <p>But then withal we ought to remember, that it is not our Faith at ſpurts and times, though never ſo lively, but 'tis our conſtancy in it, that is to bring us to work theſe Wonders: And thus it is that ſuch a Faith is only of effect, that Rules our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as with a Law; that ſtands firm, though ruffled by diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and that dares laugh at Croſſes, and whom no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Stay can fail; we muſt not, with <hi>David,</hi> againſt GOD's Command number our People, as if we would repoſe on an Arm of Fleſh; but we muſt learn with a generous freedom readily and wholly to obey the Commands of GOD, maugre all Fears and Diſappointments whatever, and then we need not fear but that in due time we ſhall even wrap up our ſelves into Immortality.</p>
               <p>And thus alſo what though thy frailty make thee to continue to ſin, yet deſpair not, but reſolve at leaſt to be good through GOD and Chriſt, nor judge thy Faith through little Doubts and tranſient Deſpairs incident to the frailty of Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, but if it has all along influenced thee to be Active and Faithful, ſcorn even all the Arts and Wiles of Satan to diſcourage thee. What, wilt thou let any Creature out-vye thy Conſtancy? Wilt thou ſee the Sun and Stars continue their courſes and luſtres in Obedience to their GOD, whilſt thou only forgoeſt thine Holy Faith and Integrity?</p>
               <p>Though as a Woman conceiving, and in Travel therefore thou art forced to bear many a bitter pang, e're thou arrive to bring forth this Son, yet at laſt doubt not but that thou wilt have him; I mean him that ſhall be able to Rule the Nations as with a Rod of Iron, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26, 27. and that will not only be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65762:13"/>able to deliver thee, with <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonas,</hi> from <hi>Goliath</hi> and the Whale's Belly, but even give thee the power of Tongues, and of feeding Multitudes too, if occaſion.</p>
               <p>But thou doubteſt thy aſſurance in theſe things: And what, cannot Examples ſatisfie thee? Surely that <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> and Chriſt after his Reſurrection were tranſlated, were Evidence enough, did we weigh matters juſtly; beſides, if we enter the Kingdom of Heaven by the reverſe of the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and as is moſt rational, can we think GOD ſo cruel, as to require the Puniſhment after the Purgation? Or can we Blaſpheme ſo, as to ſay, he has made us naturally uncapable of that Perfection he requires of us? Nay, or can we have any regard to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Chriſt, who has aſſured us, that whoever keeps his Sayings, ſhall never ſee Death, and doubt it?</p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay then? Could GOD grant theſe Favours to ſome Men only, and not be partial? Surely without we will Blaſpheme him, they are in the power of all to ſeek and have; and if ſo, what though you have few Talents, as I have ſhewn you, uſe them but well, and you have a Promiſe of Increaſe: And what though you are tempted, fear not, for from St. <hi>Paul</hi> you may learn that the Grace of GOD is ſufficient for thee. So, what though God hide his Face from thee, without thou forſakeſt him he cannot leave thee, in truth he is neareſt when ſeeming furtheſt; ſo that if thou art loſt in this matter, 'tis plain it muſt be wilfully and knowingly, and not by Accident, for otherwiſe GOD's Veracity cannot let thee fail.</p>
               <p>If thou once layeſt hold therefore on the firſt Link of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Chain, the Holy Spirit muſt needs lead thee right; and if thou purſue the other Links he ſhall carry thee to, faithfully and couragiouſly thou muſt aſcend; but if you let go or ſtop, 'tis your own fault, and you muſt expect either to fall into a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, or at beſt that the Holy Ghoſt ceaſe to raiſe you higher, and endeavour to purifie you as high as he can: Whereas if thou art but once truly and throughly prepared, thou needeſt not fear either Dangers, Misfortunes, or Temptations, for as GOD cannot but ſecure thee from them if thou relyeſt on him in them, ſo their ſeeming hazard in a perfect Faith thou mayeſt aſſure thy ſelf will but haſten thy Tryal and Victory the ſooner.</p>
               <p>Nor be concerned at the meanneſs of thy Perſon whoever thou art; for as Chriſt himſelf was a Carpenter's Son, at leaſt in Repute and Education, ſo though thou art even a Slave, GOD
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65762:14"/>will admit thee heartily a Freeman-Workman in his Kingdom; nay, he'll accept thy conſtant Meditations towards it if thou haſt no other leiſure; and no matter whether thou be Eloquent or Fooliſh in thy Addreſs, ſo thou be but ſincere, GOD like a tender Father will as well hear thy ſtammer'd Prayers as thoſe of his moſt learned Sons: We ſee by the choice of Chriſt in his Apoſtles, that none are contemptible to GOD, and that even Fiſhermen, if they have good Hearts, ſhall be preferred before either the wiſeſt or the wealthieſt.</p>
               <p>But you expect clearer grounds than theſe you ſay, for ſuch a Perfection as Tranſlation: I anſwer, was not Chriſt to be our Pattern and Example in all things? And if he was, was not he tranſlated? 'Tis true, he dyed firſt, becauſe he came purpoſely into the World to be our Sacrifice, and to obtain the Second Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9. But you ſee for all that, that Death could hold him but three days, and <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> obtained it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
               <p>And beſides, why doth Chriſt all along exhort to a powerful and operative Faith? Indeed Prophecy, Miracles, and Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeem now all equally impoſſible, but that is from the want of our Faith, or elſe why ſhould it not ſeem as poſſible for a greater Faith to attain Tranſlation, according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5. as for a leſs to reach Prophecy or Miracles? Surely it ſeems eaſier in its ſelf for GOD to keep us from Death altogether, than to raiſe Men again ſo Miraculouſly as he did, from the duſt of the Grave at the Death of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.52.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, we are naturally Mortal: And was not <hi>Adam</hi> ſo, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> who was created to ſubſiſt through eating and drinking as well as we? And if he through the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of GOD was capable of being preſerved Immortal till he fell, as ſeems the very purport of the Scriptures, have we any reaſon to deſpair the ſame Care or Power? Is either the hand of the Lord grown ſhort, or can his Loving-kindneſs ever fail us? Surely that our Lives are ſhort, as they are, is in great meaſure to be attributed to our ſelves; do we not ſee how we might prolong our Lives, if we were careful, as <hi>Galen,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others have done by their Temperance before us?</p>
               <p>With a like Reaſon alſo you wonder to ſee the Deſtructions of Death, the Ravages of War, and the Blood of Maſſacres. Alas! you ſhould rather wonder at the ſin of Men, that will not let them perfect themſelves above theſe things, and leave thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65762:14"/>ſins to the vengeance of God, that ought to be purged through our own Induſtry: While we continue under the Curſe of Sin, and have nothing in us like the Life of Faith, Death is juſtly our Portion, and what Injury is it that GOD in his Providence takes us out of the World, either ſingle, or in multitudes, as he is pleaſed to introduce any new Scene or Change in the World by it, ſince we all alike deſerve Death?</p>
               <p>And juſt ſo alſo as Infants and new-born Babes God is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in withdrawing us from the Miſeries of Life, beſides that Death is our Portion, and our common Curſe to expect, till Faith come in, and by the Power and Juſtice of GOD entitle us to Immortality: Saith the Scriptures, <hi>The day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt dye;</hi> that is, thou and thy Poſterity ſhall become Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and as we find we are; but does that imply that an exacter Purity and Obedience when we come to the Age of Diſcretion ſhall not through Faith reverſe the Curſe of <hi>Adam,</hi> and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us firſt back again into the Spiritual Paradiſe, reſtore us to the Tree of Life alſo?</p>
               <p>Chriſt indeed doth not ſeem ſo much to declare ſuch an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality the immediate effect of Faith as Miracles; but why? Becauſe he leads his Diſciples to the leſſer degrees of Faith firſt, and inſtructed them as their Capacities could bear, or elſe he doth not neglect Inſtructions even to Immortality neither; but we ſee what Encouragement ſuch a forward Truth as Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was like to meet with, when the <hi>Jews</hi> not only reviled him for pretending to it, and that he ſhould be greater than their Father <hi>Abraham</hi> that dyed, but even many of his Diſciples alſo left him upon it, <hi>John</hi> 6. And ſurely then he had great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Preach ſo forward a Doctrine ſo ſoon.</p>
               <p>Beſides he knew that as they grew more in Faith, that GOD would either reveal this to them, or that they would know it of courſe; ſo that if they but improved their growth in Spiritual Wiſdom through an exact purſuance of GOD's Holy Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 'twere impoſſible that they ſhould ever have miſcarried.</p>
               <p>Nor need we wonder that GOD has only revealed theſe Truths to thoſe that have ſo induſtriouſly ſerved him, no, and that though they were even Apoſtles; do we not ſee the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this even in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who for the ſake of <hi>Cornelius</hi> was forced to have a particular Revelation to aſſure him that GOD was no reſpecter of Perſons. So that well may we miſcarry if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65762:15"/>we take not the pains to work out our own way, what, would we have GOD alone do all for us?</p>
               <p>Let me therefore hearten you to this great Victory by that gracious Promiſe of our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26. <hi>And to him that overcometh, and keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give power over the Nations: And he ſhall Rule them with a Rod of Iron: as the Veſſels of a Potter ſhall they be broken to ſhivers, even as I received of my Father. And I will give him the Morning-ſtar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thou wanteſt immediately to be at Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Miracles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of Miracles,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and to ſee the Credentials of Prophets: Alas, beware leſt thy impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Pride hurry thee to Enthuſiaſm; remember that as thy fond Paſſions cannot raiſe thee in the Kingdom of GOD, ſo if thy Sincerity be entire, thy little involuntary lapſes of frailty cannot hurt thee; but yet as thy conſtant application in Purity will carry thee to Heaven, ſo a laſting and ſettled, proud, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Curioſity muſt needs hurry thee to Enthuſiaſm and Deluſion.</p>
               <p>What, don't we find that 'twas the Practice even of Chriſt himſelf not to attempt any thing in Faith till his time was come? Nay, was it not one of the very Temptations of the Devil to him, to ſet him preſumptuouſly to turn the Stones into Bread when he was an hungred in the Wilderneſs, before his proper ſeaſon of Miracles? Yes, ſurely it was, and that God who has ſo freely helped and delivered his Servants in their real diſtreſſes, is not leſs averſe to thoſe that have preſumptuouſly neglected his ordinary means in an Ambition of extraordinary.</p>
               <p>Learn therefore with Patience to expect thy growth as a Child, and to wait ſuch Credentials when GOD ſhall ſee fit to give them, remember that as to have them before thy time were to deſtroy thy Tryal, ſo even to deſire them were a ſin, as croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Will of GOD, and to which we ought at all times to pay the moſt entire Submiſſion: 'Tis true, GOD has promiſed us, <hi>That our Old Men ſhould dream Dreams, and that our Young Men ſhould ſee Viſions;</hi> but yet 'tis fit then that we ſhould wait the leiſure and performance of the Condition firſt.</p>
               <p>Beſides we want Revelations, Viſions, and Apparitions, but what for? Only to ask wanton Queſtions of the other World, when we forget that ſuch a Curioſity is preſumptuous, and that we ought to acquieſce wholly in hearing our Meſſage. Or what is it that we would ſeek by them, only to know our Duty?
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65762:15"/>As to that, Chriſt tells us plainly, that if we cannot believe <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, neither ſhall we one from the Dead, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.28. Should an Angel appear to us he could not alter Truth; nay, and we forget that Satan often appears as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Light: So that all we can expect from ſuch a Curioſity, is but to draw down the Deluſions of evil Angels amongſt us.</p>
               <p>So that you ſee GOD may deſervedly Puniſh this wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with a want of Viſion; we may prepare our ſelves not to be ignorant of the Voice of GOD when he ſpeaks indeed, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> were, but we are to expect to be always left and tryed in doubts whilſt we reſt in the Pilgrimage and Wilderneſs of this World: Indeed it has been the common condition of the Juſt to live by Faith, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. and till Death or Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we muſt not expect a certainty or perfection. What, is not our very Being in Fleſh, as the Apoſtle ſays, by deſign alſo to be as abſent for the Lord?</p>
               <p>And thus, had not Chriſt himſelf his hours of Temptation as well as Viſion, and ſhall we pretend to an Exemption? No, we muſt expect them in all ſtates; till our ſtate of Prophecy, indeed our Tryals are more dark, as encountring chiefly a bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Infidelity, but after that, even in Revelation, they are not leſs dangerous, and when, like Chriſt, and <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> we are turned looſe to the Perſonal Wiles of Satan.</p>
               <p>But you would know how Dreams and Viſions are to be known and truſted: As to that you muſt beware of a preſumptuous Curioſity of all kinds,<note place="margin">Of Dreams and Viſions.</note> for in thoſe things you gamble out of the Road of GOD; and therefore if he leave you to Evil Angels, you need not wonder: And ſo in all other Methods, whereby you ſhall ſhew your ſelf uneaſie at the leiſure of GOD's Tryals, you ought to dread your ſtate for fear of ſome dreadful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Enthuſiaſm.</p>
               <p>But if on the contrary you know your ſelf Innocent in your Conſcience from ſuch a Preſumption, you need not fear but that whatſoever Dream or Viſion you have that appears to be good, muſt come from GOD, and as it Commands you, you ought to obey it; for as the Scriptures declare, that GOD of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten leads Men by Dreams, ſo that plainly implies, that he requires us to obey them where he gives them; and why ſhould we be in any danger in the caſe? Cannot GOD ſecure us from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65762:16"/>of Dreams as well as he has done from the other Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and bodily Injuries of Satan, if we forfeit not his care?</p>
               <p>And hence it is that GOD will be plain with us beyond preſumption, where he requires ſuch Obedience; nay, if his Meſſage be ſurprizing or extraordinary, as he did to <hi>Moſes,</hi> he will give thee a Miracle rather than fail to confirm thee in it; but be ſure then he will never Command thee to do a Moral Evil, to reject Humanity, or to commit Barbarities, ſuch are Deluſions, under what colour ſoever of Revelation they may appear.</p>
               <p>Nay, and that ſuch Divine Aſſiſtances are not quite Novelties even in our Ages, you have not only Biſhop <hi>Uſher</hi>'s, and <hi>Withers</hi>'s, but the Eminent Judge <hi>Hales</hi>'s Authority to aſſure you, and yet not but that though ſuch are Bleſſings which GOD may give us in Grace and Mercy to ſupport us, yet they are not to be expected, much leſs deſired, without the greateſt Submiſſion and Reſignation to the Will of GOD imaginable.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> were ſick of this Curioſity, and deſired Signs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end; and even we alſo, were we humoured to ſee an Angel once, in a little time ſhould have the ſame Curioſity again, and to what end? Only to furniſh our ſelves with ſo many Stories, and to bring ſuch Sacred Benefits into Contempt, or to reſent to GOD how uneaſie we are at the Trayals he has ſet us here, and contrary to his declared Will how fierce we are for Fruition and Perfection.</p>
               <p>Alas! not only when it pleaſes GOD to bleſs us with ſuch Private Revelations, they are deſigned wholly for our private and ſingular Comfort, but we are both preſumptuous and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, without ſpecial Order to publiſh them; for what is it to another the private Evidences of Grace and Favours that have happened between GOD and our ſelves? Nay, and do we not follow the Example of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this, who you ſee would never reveal the extraordinary private Viſions that he declares he had, in his Epiſtles.</p>
               <p>And juſt with as much Reaſon is it that we are endleſly vain in our deſires of ſuch things, we forget our Preſumption in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring more of GOD than his Wiſdom ſees fit; was GOD ever Prodigal of his Viſions to any of his Prophets? Or did he give them rather rarely, and as his Love to them or Mankind required? And if not, what is it we aim at? A Prerogative a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove whatever any other enjoyed before us, and what is beyond
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65762:16"/>thoſe fixed Bounds of Tryal which GOD has ſet for the beſt in this World?</p>
               <p>But to return, how many are there that on the contrary, like the unbelieving Lord at <hi>Samaria,</hi> are trod under foot in their growth, through their Infidelity? And ſo haughtily obſtructing the firſt entrance of the Holy Ghoſt, cut off all their hopes of their Progreſs in Piety; I may ſay, can you expect that GOD ſhould proceed otherwiſe than gradually with you, and not truſt you with greater Talents, but according as you manage your leſs? And if you can't, as he dealt not otherwiſe with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prophets, how do you think to walk by Faith if you ſink the firſt ſtep you go?</p>
               <p>We have ſundry Examples in Scripture, both in the Old and New Teſtament, of Dreams, ſome plain, and ſome Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical, wherein GOD has required Men to pay him Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but eſpecially in <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet. I ſay therefore, if ſuch Prophetical Dreams are only diſcernable from others by the Rules I have before ſhewn, 'tis plain then that where we find Dreams within ſuch limitations, we ought to obey them in every thing that is not evil; nay, and that with our greateſt Skill, and without Tempting GOD to an unneceſſary Miracle where he Commands us.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay? Some Men by a bold Aſſertion, and a Spirit of Infidelity, will not only tell you, that all Dreams are meerly Melancholy Fancies, and thence neither diſcernable good from bad, nor regardable, but more, that they may level us in common to Bruits, they tell us, that even Dogs dream: And though themſelves ſee that Dreams are involuntary, and out of the power of the Soul, yet the better to flatter their own Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, whether with Reaſon or without, 'tis all one to them, they attribute all meerly to the power of Nature.</p>
               <p>But methinks it ſhould be convincing enough to any Man in this caſe, to ſee that all Men Dream not, and that none can Command the time or thing they dream of; ſo that GOD af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us but rarely Commanding or Active Dreams, becauſe as good ones we deſerve them not, and as evil ones in Mercy he protects us from them; indeed in our Dreams he often lets Satan tempt us by our Luſts and Fears, and the Fathers of old have taught us to Pray againſt ſuch his Evils, but that always in ſuch a giddy and incoherent manner, that it ſpeaks its ſelf a Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and from the Devil.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65762:17"/>
               <p>And laſtly, That the Evil Angels ſhould give Bruits Dreams to cheriſh us in our Infidelity, ſeems no more ſtrange to me, than that GOD once opened the mouth of an Aſſe; for if not only GOD is ſo careful of his Creation, as not to let an hair of our Heads, or a Sparrow fall without his knowledge, but even the Devil is ſo indefatigably Active to Torment Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as rather than fail, to enter into a Serpent to tempt us: Can we think, I ſay, among other Stratagems he would not ſtoop even to give Dogs Dreams alſo, when by it he can give ſo good an Argument and Support for Atheiſm? And yet even this Satan cannot do without leave, we ſee he could not enter the Herd of Swine, much leſs ſhall we ſuppoſe him able to delude or poſſeſs a Man without expreſs Authority from GOD?</p>
               <p>But methinks I hear it objected, What Guard have we then againſt Enthuſiaſm? I ſay, as good as is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with GOD's Juſtice,<note place="margin">Of Enthuſiaſm.</note> and our Tryals: The Scriptures tell us, that the Devil often ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears as an Angel of Light, but that does not ſhew that therefore we have no Power through God's Grace to diſcern him; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed through our Pride, or other fault, GOD may leave us, and ſo we may be deluded; or elſe 'tis impoſſible: So that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed 'tis juſtly to our Perils not to diſcover Faith from Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Revelation from Enthuſiaſm, nay, and 'tis what God may moſt juſtly require at our hands.</p>
               <p>In Enthuſiaſm the Faith is excellent and ſtrong, but the edge or end of it is perverted, ſo that any Man may eaſily judge whether he is in Enthuſiaſm or not; if in his Zeal he errs wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, 'tis fatal; but if ignorantly, like St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> he need not fear but that GOD will rather by a Miracle ſave our Son, and Convert us, than let us ſuffer damage; but then if with the Jewiſh Exorciſts, and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> with the love of the World in our hearts, we ſeek to hold the Truth in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, methinks we have no reaſon to complain that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires have ſucceeded againſt us, and we are loſt in Enthuſiaſm.</p>
               <p>And yet not but that there are extreams on the other ſide too; there are Men that lye dead in Forms as well as ſuch as are mad in Superſtition, and that have not Patience for their Tryals; nor are they leſs to be reproved for burying their Talents, than the others for making every whimſey that croſſes their Thoughts to come from GOD; I muſt confeſs the latter is chiefly proper to my Subject here, and yet the former alſo ſtands juſtly in my way of Reproof.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65762:17"/>
               <p>To return therefore, how eaſie a Teſt have we againſt any man's pretence for feeling Truth? Alas! GOD's Holy Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and right Reaſon are never diſcernable aſunder, we are only to know Trees by their Fruits, and not to believe even an Angel from Heaven, if he Preach other Doctrine than Truth; what hazard are we at then, whether a Man be an Enthuſiaſt or not, if we follow him with a blind implicit Submiſſion, indeed we are, but we ought to be always on our Guard, and to have ſuch a Reſpect for no man's Perſon.</p>
               <p>And thus though 'twere the Devil that perſwaded or convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me of my Duty, as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Luther,</hi> I would not neglect it, not but that I would periſh too before that I would ſeek to him for it: And on the contrary, were I ſure he were an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel or a Prophet that perſwaded me to what I knew, or but thought in my Conſcience to be evil, I would certainly diſobey him.</p>
               <p>What danger have we then left of falling into Deluſions? Or what good will even the confidence of a Mountebank do our feeling Enthuſiaſts? Alas, nothing but betray them. GOD's Spirit is meek and lowly, he tells us, that he reſiſts the Proud: And hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays modeſtly in one place of his Epiſtles, that he believes only that he has the Spirit of GOD, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.40.</p>
               <p>And had not our new Spirit Men, that I am perſwaded have not his Warrant, better ſay ingenuouſly then, that their Silence and Meditation leaves room for that Holy Spirit, whoſe Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they hope they may have, at leaſt in ſome degree, rather than by an haughty and proud Arrogance thus burſt the growth of thoſe Holy Seeds, that ought only to be cheriſhed through Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility? Nay, and do not they as good as grant this, when they not only ſay, they do, but even we ſee that they err groſly in their beſt Exerciſes?</p>
               <p>If you will be free therefore of Enthuſiaſm, beware of this Pride, and beware of a proud and needleſs Separation from others on the too common, but groundleſs pretences that we are more Holy than you. 'Twas propheſied of old, that we ſhould not be able to endure ſound Doctrine, but heap up to our ſelves Teachers having itching Ears, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. But remember 'tis no ſlight Offence to forſake a Publick Church too eaſily, 'twas what all the Corruptions of the Jews could not make Chriſt do, who always Taught in their Synagogues and Temples, <hi>John</hi> 18.20.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65762:18"/>Publick Communion is ſo Sacred a Bond, <hi>Heb:</hi> 10.26. that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I know but flat Idolatry, with <hi>Elijah, Shadrack, Meſhack,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> is able to excuſe thee from it.</p>
               <p>Beſides conſider how many GOD has laid his Judgments on for this ſeparating Pride, and how he has often let the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil inſpire them inſtead of the Holy Ghoſt; nay, and remember too that Chriſt made it his buſineſs to converſe with Sinners, and thou for all thy Pride art but a Man, and much meaner ſure than he; and if ſo, as all Mankind are thy Brethren, at worſt they require thy Advice and Reproof; and fear not, like <hi>Lot;</hi> thou wilt not be the ſooner deſtroy'd for living amongſt them, if thou continueſt pure thy ſelf; but if having but a ſeeming Holineſs thou glory in a proud and uncharitable Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, know that Deluſion will ruine thee. The Soul that has not a Love, Faith, and Purity as large as GOD's, at leaſt in good will, has not his Spirit.</p>
               <p>By what has been wrote therefore I think it is plain, that our diſcerning of Spirits is no ſuch Work to be deſpair'd at as is ſuppos'd if we keep our ſelves but pure: Our Wickedneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed may forfeit God's Protection of us, or elſe we may be ſure he will not let us be fool'd out of the Glory that he has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for us: And thus as GOD ordinarily has appeared to his Prophets both by Dreams and Viſions, and as he did to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradice; ſo he requires our Obedience to them alſo as he has done with them, and as well he may where he has done but the ſame to others; and I ſay, it is juſtly alſo even at our Peril to diſcern Faith from Preſumption in them, ſince we cannot be deceiv'd but thro' our own fault and neglect.</p>
               <p>As I have ſaid before, Certainty and Perfection belong only to Tranſlation and Fruition; not, I mean, that if we truſt wholly in God we are at any hazard neither; as GOD has promis'd us not to let us be tempted beyond our Strength, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. And ſurely we may let GOD be true, tho' every Man be a Lyar: But we muſt learn from thence to abate all overweening Pride, and for our own Safety in purſuance of our Trials, to reſign our ſelves wholly and entirely to the Will of GOD.</p>
               <p>And thus had the Magicians exceeded <hi>Moſes</hi> in Wonders as much as there were hundreds of <hi>Baalites</hi> to one <hi>Elijah,</hi> yet <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> (tho' the only Prophets of GOD left) muſt needs be diſcernable thro' their Sincerity: And that Man or Prophet that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65762:18"/>ſhall unſincerely and diſobediently hearken even to a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet againſt his known Duty and Conſcience, ſhall have a Lion provided to tear him in pieces in his way as he returns; and as even the Scriptures themſelves have given us in Example.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, we may conclude upon the whole matter, that not only if we obey not the leſſer and firſt tendings of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, we are weak to expect the greater, but we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous alſo if we ſeek greater certainty than others have had before us. Suppoſe I am to obey GOD on theſe terms, do I hazard more than others have done before me? And thus could it be any thing but the Innocence of <hi>Moſes</hi> in his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that could aſſure him that the Angel that appeared unto him in the Buſh, was not other than an Angel of Light? And ſhall I expect then to truſt GOD on ſurer grounds? And even ſo in Natural Religion alſo, I have full as good a Warrant in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an upright Conſcience as the beſt of Prophets can have in following his Revelation.</p>
               <p>Further, by what has been wrote alſo, we may ſee what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Regard we are to pay even the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelves.<note place="margin">Of Scripture.</note> Thus in whatever words the Prophets or Apoſtles wrote, as they had them from ſome Viſion or Revelation, or from Chriſt, we ought to pay them an abſolute regard, as coming immediately from the Spirit of GOD himſelf; but whatever Truths they delivered prudentially, and as from their own Reaſoning, we ought to take them as ſuch, and wherein we have the Advice of the moſt Holy and Sincere Men, and as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf acquaints us.</p>
               <p>And hence alſo we ſee plainly that the Apoſtles not only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to ſtudy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. and underſtood Chriſt's words by degrees, as the Spirit occaſionally operating with their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning explained them, but even in their Citations out of the Old Teſtament, they both truſted their Memories, and rather regarded ſenſe than words; and hence St. <hi>Matthew</hi> cites <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> for <hi>Zechariah;</hi> and hence St. <hi>Luke</hi> is ſo modeſt, that in the very beginning of his Goſpel he rather ſhews you that he writes to be credited as a fair Witneſs, than one that in every word would Command you by an Infallible Inſpiration.</p>
               <p>Not that I would inſinuate hereby by any means neither (as the Judicious <hi>Lowth</hi> in this caſe has very well obſerved) as if the Inſpiration of Holy Writ were imperfect, or that the Scriptures
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65762:19"/>were not a moſt perfect Rule of Faith: Surely he's mad, that once believes the Hiſtory of the Apoſtles Miracles, can ever think their Doctrines were not thereby confirmed by God: But whether ſuch Teſtimony of God muſt argue their Inſpiration <hi>Verbatim,</hi> or their Inſtruction of us to a literal Infallibility (as he likewiſe obſerves) let the Reader judge.</p>
               <p>Nay, and beſides I may add, for the Holy Ghoſt to have made the Prophets and Evangeliſts his Secretaries <hi>Verbatim,</hi> would not only have done violence to their Tryals, but were to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe neither: For what needed he to have ſhewn-thoſe things by Revelation, that Reaſon could find out? So alſo if he had dictated to them <hi>Verbatim,</hi> as Truth is one, and Wiſdom is one in Perfection, ſo it were impoſſible that there ſhould be a letter varying in what they wrote; nay, and if he had, why ſhould we think of them, that they ſhould rather only Hiſtorically deliver the Precepts of Chriſt then, than diſpoſe them in order, and as from themſelves, had not they thought that his Authority in giving them was greater than their own?</p>
               <p>And ſo what but this Fallibility was it, may I ſay, made the Apoſtles meet together to diſpute in Council, had they, like the Prophets in their particular Meſſages, gotten GOD's immediate Inſtructions in all things? One had ſpoke the Mind of all, and there could never have been any occaſion to aſſemble to diſpute, ſince they could never vary in Judgment, but like our Saviour, who had the Spirit without meaſure, they would have proceeded on in Eternal paths of Love, Truth, and Unity.</p>
               <p>Nor is their Credit even as thus, and from their very Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity little, as it is, as a Heathen reflected, when he read their Morals, <hi>I wiſh all the World had believed them.</hi> So indeed they have ſuch an Integrity, that they cannot but command a Reſpect where ever they come. And as for their Errors and mutual leſſer Variances, they rather benefit than injure them; for where there is a fallible Integrity that varies in Trifles, and agrees in the Main, it even luſtres Truth, by cutting off the very grounds of all Suſpicion and Confederacy.</p>
               <p>We ought therefore always to remember, as well in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Apoſtles as Prophets, rather to follow their ſincere ſenſe and purport, than their Grammatical and forced Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for not only the Apoſtles, as I have ſhewn you, have cited the Old Teſtament by their Memories, but even the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets alſo, as <hi>Luther</hi> obſerves in his Table-talk, <hi>p.</hi> 362. had none of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65762:19"/>their Revelations <hi>Verbatim,</hi> but when they delivered their Viſions, did it in their own way, and their own ſtile and words; thus one as a Noble, and another as a Husbandman, and if they had any Expreſſions immediately from God, 'twas very rarely.</p>
               <p>And hence alſo you ſee that the Prophets were ſo far from an abſolute Inſpiration, or a perfect Freedom with GOD, that very often they could ſcarce underſtand the dark and Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphical Propheſies they received themſelves, and whether they did at all in ſome caſes, I will not determine; for though all Propheſies can have but one clear, ſincere, rational, and cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent meaning; as Truth, eſpecially in the Fountain, is not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and as ſo they were dictated by GOD to be underſtood one time or other; yet it does not follow therefore that they muſt underſtand them, for ſurely he may juſtly reſerve their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to what Time or Seaſon he ſhall think beſt.</p>
               <p>Nor is this an inconſiderable Leſſon that we may learn from a due conſideration in this matter, for ſurely it muſt make no ſmall tendency to the Progreſs of the true Goſpel-Precepts and Piety, to cut off all occaſion of little Capricio's and Criticiſm; the great and main Leſſon of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and what was truly confirmed from God by Miracles, is too well and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely delivered, to be injured by little Cavils, or the variance of Copies.</p>
               <p>But to return, as to what may be more particularly ſaid rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the ſtate of Prophecy, we may add, that,<note place="margin">The State of Prophecy.</note> as I have before obſerved, <hi>Adam</hi> was to ſtand a while e're he became tranſlated; and if ſo ſince the degradation of our Fall, we may well expect even to ſtand a further Tryal alſo, e're we become Prophets; thus Chriſt was near Thirty e're he entred his firſt Stage, and <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> not young when they were tranſlated, and can we expect otherwiſe then? Nor need we to be diſmay'd though we have no notice of our being either to be Prophets or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, had <hi>Adam</hi> either ſuch notice in Paradiſe, or <hi>Elijah</hi> almoſt to the very day?</p>
               <p>Nor is it unworthy Obſervation in this caſe how like and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel the courſe of <hi>Moſes, Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> has been. Say the Scriptures, <hi>Moſes</hi> is not a Prophet in dark Dreams, and Viſions only, but God ſpoke clearly, and Face to Face to him, and did he not ſo to Chriſt and <hi>Elijah</hi> alſo? So how exactly likewiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt agreed in their Transfiguration, and Chriſt and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65762:20"/>
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> in their Miracles; one raiſed the Dead, and ſo did the other; the one multiplyed and fed with Bread miraculouſly, and ſo did the other; the one was tranſlated, and the other aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heaven within a very few days after his Death, nor had he dyed, had it not been fore-ordered.</p>
               <p>Nor could they that would have imitated theſe Patterns have failed, had they taken more care to have purified themſelves, and to have been more curious in that one and eaſie Rule, to chooſe the good, and avoid the ill, think you elſe that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> might not have been tranſlated as well as <hi>Elijah</hi> a Jew; had they but laid by their Animoſities, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.37. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. and other faults, for ſurely both as Chriſtians they could not deſerve leſs, and Tranſlation in its ſelf muſt needs be more for the Honour both of GOD and Chriſtianity, than Martyrdom.</p>
               <p>But what, you are offended that I take theſe Liberties with the Apoſtles; you forget that though they had the Spirit, yet was it but in part; they knew in part, and they propheſied in part; nay, and their Gifts ſometimes vaniſhed away: So you forget that even the very beſt of them were forced to work out their Salvations with fear and trembling, for all their gifts; nor need I ſay thus on preſumption only, for do not the Scriptures ſay the ſame thing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8, 9. And do they not ſhew us, that they that had the Gifts of Tongues, did ſometimes abuſe them? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>God is not laviſh in his Gifts, though he is liberal; ſo that though he give his Graces on occaſion, yet he ſuits them to Times and Seaſons of his own; nay, and though by us he informs the World of their Duty, yet he takes care withal by his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion never to give us ſuch a certainty as may deſtroy our Tryals, by Faith, and from this Fallibility it was that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ordered the Spirit of the Prophets to be ſubject to the Prophets, and that he adviſed <hi>Timothy</hi> to Study and Reading, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. and prudentially to drink Water with his Wine. Indeed, as I have ſaid, what need had the Apoſtles and Prophets of a <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim</hi> and Council, if that they had had all things immediately inſpired from GOD?</p>
               <p>In truth, if we would but open our Eyes, we might ſee theſe matters beyond doubt: Thus nothing is plainer than that <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> knew not Chriſt by ſight, though he knew of him by Revelation. So nothing is more evident than that St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65762:20"/>could call the High-Prieſt a whited Wall in a miſtake, for all that he had Chriſt's particular Promiſe to be helped before Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, this Argument needs no other Evidence, unleſs it be for thoſe whom none can convince. Shall the Scriptures tell us, that even the Angels are impure in the ſight of GOD, and ſhall we be afraid to charge Men with faults? Indeed could Chriſt himſelf be in ſuch doubts, as to want an Angel to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, and to cry out, <hi>My GOD, my GOD, why haſt thou forſaken me,</hi> upon the Croſs? And may we not charge his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with weakneſſes?</p>
               <p>But to proceed, not only ſingle Perſons, but even Churches alſo may arrive at the ſtate of Prophecy,<note place="margin">Of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Churches.</note> if they are but Pious accordingly: Thus what were the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> but a Generation of Prophets? And had they not been rebellious, inſtead of their periſhing in the Wilderneſs, and their having a Ceremonial Law, and an Earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> as a School-Maſter to bring them to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. who can doubt but that they might and would have arrived there themſelves?</p>
               <p>And hence methinks I dare rationally Prophecy, That if ever any Government ſhall heartily ſeek to GOD, and by a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Reformation, and Addreſs through Prayers ſeek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of GOD, they ſhall not only be able, like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to divide the Red-Sea for their Paſſage, and to have their Cloaths not wax old, and Quails ſent them by GOD himſelf, rather than fail, to nouriſh them if occaſion be, but they ſhall even almoſt infinitely exceed their Type in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and by degrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more Glorious than now our very Thoughts can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
               <p>Then, as the Prophets have foretold us of old, will the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py time arrive, <hi>when Nation ſhall no longer riſe againſt Nation;</hi> nay, <hi>when the Lion and the Lamb ſhall be able to lye down together in ſafety; then ſhall our Swords be beaten into Plow-ſhears, and our Spears into Pruning-hooks, while Truth and Peace ſhall kiſs each other, and Righteouſneſs ſhall even run down our Streets in that Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That, when e're it comes, will be Chriſt's Glorious Day, and that which <hi>Abraham</hi> rejoyced to ſee: That will be the time the Devils dreaded ſo long ſince, when they asked Chriſt, whether he was come to torment them before their time? That will be what muſt needs end in the Glorious Sabbath, which St. <hi>John</hi> by the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65762:21"/>
                  <hi>Revelations</hi> leads the Churches to, and of which though as yet we have no demonſtrable Interpretation, yet the very Glympſe we have of it, is enough to encourage us towards it, though without a preciſe Reſolution.</p>
               <p>But in ſhort, what-ever Church aims at this, muſt do it hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, or elſe 'twill be all in vain; for until they have wholly laid by their Self-love, and ſeek purely for the Glory of GOD, they can never rationally expect ſo peculiar a care from GOD, for ſurely in this the Poet is right, <hi>Veniunt ad Candida tecta co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor wonder at theſe things, for if <hi>Withers</hi> prove a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, as hitherto he has been, there muſt be ſuch a change in the Church as this e're long; and that you may the better know how you are to expect it, I ſhall add theſe few Verſes, taken out of his late Collection of Propheſies, and that were Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Convention in the Year 1689.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Pag. 3.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And then ſhall Righteouſneſs aſcend the Throne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then Truth, and Love, and Peace re-enter ſhall;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then Faith and Reaſon ſhall agree in one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And all the Vertues to their Council call.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And timely out of all theſe ſhall ariſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Kingdom, and that Happy Government,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which is the ſcope of all theſe Propheſies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That future Truths obſcurely repreſent.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Pag. 20.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be patient therefore, ye that are oppreſt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This Generation ſhall not paſs away,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till ſome behold the Downfal of the Beaſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Pag. 30.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But if that whereof ſome imperfect views</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Far off appears, accordingly enſues;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There will to thwart their hopes, a new Star blaze</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within the Weſt, which will the World amaze,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65762:21"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And influence through the Univerſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So quickly and prodigiouſly diſperſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That aided by concurring Conſtellations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It will have ſome effect upon moſt Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And cauſe ſuch Changes, as will make a ſtand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To thoſe Attempts that they have now in hand.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Meaning the Papiſts. See the Prophecy at large.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But not to rely on <hi>Withers</hi> only, do not the Scriptures ſay the ſame thing? Does not <hi>Daniel</hi> Crown all with this Kingdom of GOD at laſt? <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. And does not Chriſt tell us, that the Goſpel of the Kingdom ſhall be Preached to all the World, and then ſhall the End come, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.10. Nay, and do not the <hi>Revelations</hi> end in the ſame manner, with an Angel to Preach the Goſpel to every Nation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. and with a New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to deſcend from GOD?</p>
               <p>Indeed becauſe the Scribes were ſo wicked, as to ſhut up the Kingdom of GOD, ſo as neither to go in themſelves, nor let others enter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. Inſomuch that Chriſt ſays of them for their perverſeneſs, that the Publicans and Harlots entred the Kingdom of Heaven before them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.31. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of GOD was given from the Jews to another Nation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43. and whereupon they have been accurſed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed throughout the World, as we ſee even at this day.</p>
               <p>But can that be any diſcouragement to us? Should it not rather move us to be that Happy Nation that ſhould take their place? But then, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> warns us alſo, we ought to walk humbly upon it, leſt we that are grafted in the place whence the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Branches are cut off, ſhould upon our becoming unfruitful, be cut off alſo. GOD has performed his Promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> though many Ages after, and bleſſed all the Nations of the Earth through him; nay, and bleſſed his Seed in their <hi>Canaan.</hi> Let us not deſpair then, and he will be as good to us if we obey him; if not, we may reaſonably expect his Curſe, or worſe, on the ſlighting of his offers.</p>
               <p>But further, have we not the Apoſtle's Word for our happy Succeſs in Tranſlation, if we proceed thus? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. where he tells us, <hi>We ſhall not all dye, but be changed.</hi> And as he more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſhews us, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.17. where he tells us, <hi>That we ſhall be caught up alive to meet the Lord in the Air:</hi> And indeed as if the Criſis of Purity ſhould haſten that of Impurity, till at laſt the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65762:22"/>force of the firſt draw down Judgments on the other, and that ſaying ſhould be fulfilled thereby, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>That the wicked one ſhould be deſtroyed by the brightneſs of Chriſt's coming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, I have added this other Prophecy alſo, taken out of the ſame Book, to ſhew that GOD has even deſigned this Happy Nation for this Bleſſing; I have only repeated that part of it which is to my purpoſe, and GOD grant to bleſs us with the Succeſs of it, and which he will certainly do, if we do not obſtruct his Mercies, and ſo let down his new <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> amongſt us.</p>
               <lg>
                  <head>The Verſes are theſe.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſince Men wandring in a Wood by Night,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When they ſhall through a glade behold ſome light,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Take thereby Courage to walk chearly on,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In hope their Fears and Toyls are nearly gone.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'le from a Cloud flaſh out a little gleam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Lightning, and diſcloſe a little Beam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whereby on you a glimmering ſhall be caſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of what you may attain to at the laſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For I will ſhew you by what Pedigree</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Government to you deriv'd ſhall be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which will at laſt the</hi> Britiſh <hi>Iſlands bleſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With inward Peace, and outward Happineſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It was of late a brief preſage of his,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who oft hath Truth fore-told, and it is this,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>After all, I know no other Objection to be made in this matter,<note place="margin">Objections Hiſtorical.</note> but that theſe things are rather figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative than real; and that all Examples of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have been rather Diſpenſations of Providence by way of ſingular Favour, than true and deſigned Objects for our Imitation: But ſurely ſuch an Objection as this has but little weight in it, when duly conſidered, however popular and fair it may appear in its ſelf.</p>
               <p>And I have the rather ſtated this Objection here, becauſe I know it to be the Epidemick and Reigning Error of the Age; the common Vogue runs, Miracles are ceas'd, the Light of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is extinguiſh'd; and ſo far they are right, as they mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly are through the wickedneſs of the Age. But, ſay they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65762:22"/>further, this our Darkneſs, alas, is no other than what was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned us all along; all our Glorious Diſpenſations were but for a ſeaſon, and for the better and more ſure eſtabliſhment of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. But ſurely in this they are out, or elſe neither the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Scriptures nor Hiſtory were to be regarded, which have both expreſly delivered us the contrary.</p>
               <p>Thus, do we conſult Scripture, what is more evident than that GOD all along diſtributed his Gifts without reſpect of Perſons, and that throughout all Ages; if we begin with <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, 'tis not many Generations e're we come to <hi>Enoch,</hi> and after that to <hi>Noah:</hi> And ſo if we paſs by the Ages of the Flood, how ſoon appears the Holy <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> and the ſeries of Prophets in <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe, I may add, appears the great Luminary <hi>Moſes,</hi> who indeed almoſt made a Nation of Prophets after him; but think you he alone, and his Contemporaries had ſuch peculiar Favours for the ſake of his Revelation? No, a whole Series of Prophets reaches even from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſt; and ſcarce a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury paſſed, but what ſome Pious <hi>Jew</hi> or other prov'd as a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſiſtant to the decaying Faith of the World. Indeed for ſome time before our Saviour's Birth an Univerſal Spiritual Darkneſs begun to over-ſpread the Earth, and as well the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as the <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> began to diſappear; but ſurely the gloomy Night was fully anſwered by the Glorious dawning of the Sun of Righteouſneſs, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Hitherto therefore I think we may well conclude, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Holy Scriptures are falſe, or that neither Miracles nor Prophecy ever really ceaſed, or were deſigned to do ſo: I will not ſay, but that it may ſeem from hence as if Mankind at times has been ſo blind and wicked, that we have had few of the more Illuſtrious Saints of GOD, and that the Infidelity of Mankind has ſeemed to drown us in Night, till the more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Diſpenſations of GOD's Providence have opened our Eyes: But if ſuch be our caſe, and as it really ſeems to be no other, let us truly learn to Reaſon aright, and to vindicate the Juſtice of GOD, rather than our ſelves in ſuch our Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>But to paſs by all theſe more Illuſtrious tracks of the Grace of God in Holy Writ, and thoſe ſtupendious Wonders that were wrought by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, let us examine a little how after-ages followed: I muſt confeſs we cannot expect the ſame
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65762:23"/>Authority for what we write in this caſe, as what we could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Scriptures, becauſe we have no ſuch Evidences ſince for our Proof; but ſurely otherwiſe, if Hiſtory may be believed, or if the Credit of beſt of Writers may be regarded, the Ages after Chriſt have no more wanted their Luminaries, than thoſe after <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, ſhall we conſult <hi>Euſebius,</hi> he tells you, not only that Holy <hi>Pelycarp, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. was warned by Viſion of his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom by Fire, dreaming the Night before that his Pillow was on fire under him, but that when he came to the Stake, a Voice was heard audibly from Heaven, to bid him be of good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, the better to ſupport him under his Martyrdom. Or if you want other paſſages of the power of Faith in the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, read but his <hi>lib.</hi> the 5th. and <hi>cap.</hi> the 5th. and he acquaints you of the Lightning Legion, that even drew down Rain from GOD through their Prayers.</p>
               <p>Nor is this all that <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us of; does he not alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us in his Life of <hi>Conſtantine, Cap.</hi> 22, 23. that a Croſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared publickly in the Air to his Army, with this Inſcription, <hi>In hoc ſigno vinces?</hi> Nay, and does not <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. acquaint us with the ſame? Beſides that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had his continual Divine Warnings by Dreams and Viſions, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him from his Enemies.</p>
               <p>But for once too I will grant, that theſe great and celebrated Wonders were done to uſher in the firſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and to Congratulate Happy Chriſtianity in the Throne; for this was done full Three Hundred Years after Chriſt, and therefore ſurely cannot juſtly be eſteemed as in part of the Apoſtolick Age. I ſay therefore, ſuppoſe that ſuch were the occaſions of theſe Miracles, yet cannot the ſucceeding Ages parallel them.</p>
               <p>Let us trace the Times therefore on a little; <hi>Socrates Schol.</hi> aquaints us, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. that ſuch another Croſs appeared to <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the <hi>Arrian. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. That one was delivered by a Miracle from Priſon. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. That whilſt one <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> was ſuffering, an Angel ſtood by him, and relieved, and eaſed the pains of his ſtripes. <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. That whilſt a <hi>Jew</hi> was baptized, he was healed of his Palſie. And <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. That whilſt a counterfeit <hi>Jew</hi> was about to be baptized, the Water vaniſhed.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65762:23"/>
               <p>But why ſhould I ſtand thus as on the brinks of the Miracles related by <hi>Socrates?</hi> Does he not, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. acquaint us, how <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was once Garriſon'd by Angels againſt their Enemies? And <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 18. how another time the deſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Citizens of the ſame City were acquainted even by Angels alſo of the Victory over their Enemies.</p>
               <p>Nay, does he not in another place ſurprize us with a Wonder even greater than all theſe together? As <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. How that when <hi>Julian</hi> would have ſet the <hi>Jews</hi> about building again their Temple, Miraculous Fires appeared, and deſtroyed all their Tools and Foundations; and Croſſes like the Sun appeared on the Workmens Cloaths, by no means for a long time to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, in terror to their Proceedings, and in utter diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Attempts.</p>
               <p>Nor need I reſt here; what, cannot I as juſtly proceed to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Centuries for the ſeveral ſucceſſive Wonders of Faith? Thus, does not <hi>Evagrius Scholaſticus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. acquaint us of the Miracles of <hi>Zoſimas</hi> and <hi>Chuſubites?</hi> And ſo, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. does he not acquaint us of Confeſſors, that had their very Tongues cut out, and yet continued ſtill to ſpeak, and that throughout the whole City of <hi>Conſtantinople?</hi> And ſo, does he not, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. acquaint us of Martyrs Tombs even Miraculouſly and Divinely perfum'd.</p>
               <p>But above all, when we conſider his Wonders related of Holy <hi>Simeon,</hi> and his ſeveral Miracles related, <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 33, 34, 35. and <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. together with the Prodigies of his Apparition and Star that were ſeen about his Pillar after his Death, as he acquaints us, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. Surely we have no reaſon but to conclude, That GOD at all times hears thoſe that diligently ſerve him; and that neither Time nor Perſons are exempt from the Bleſſings of his Grace, unleſs they voluntarily incapacitate themſelves from receiving them.</p>
               <p>Nay, and beſides theſe things, I could acquaint you of others not leſs conſiderable, even from other Teſtimonies: What ſhall we ſay to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> does not he acquaint us of at leaſt Seventy Miracles done in his Times? Does he not aſſure us, that he was cured of the Tooth-ach through Prayer himſelf, and that two Blind Men received their ſight only through the touch of the Bodies of two deceaſed Martyrs?</p>
               <p>So what ſhall we ſay to the Viſions of <hi>Curma,</hi> the Miracles he mentions done publickly in Churches through Prayer? I may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65762:24"/>ſay, what can we make of the infinite other foot-ſteps of Faith, that the other Holy Fathers and Writers have left behind them? Can nothing of what they relate be eſteemed for Truth? And muſt we ſtill be of that brutiſh ſenſe, that 'tis rather the Will of GOD than our own Defects that keeps us from following ſuch Glorious Patterns before us?</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, Reader, I have given thee a Summary trace in this matter to the Sixth Century, and I hope to thy SAtisfaction; I will not ſay, that in theſe latter Ages GOD has left himſelf entirely without a Witneſs; for undoubtedly I might juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thee an agreeable Series of the Mercies of GOD, at leaſt in ſome leſſer degrees, even to our days, witneſs the Delivery of <hi>Melancton,</hi> and the Prayers for Rain of <hi>Luther.</hi> But ſince I have brought thee as far as the brink of Popery, and as long as our preſent Churches will allow the paſt Catholick, I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf in deſiſting the further Labour.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole, I know nothing left to be diſputed in this caſe but the Credit of Hiſtories; and as for that, I ſhall little concern my ſelf: If the Diſpute be, whether the Gifts of GOD were ever deſigned to ceaſe, and undoubted Hiſtory be not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon it, I ſhall never trouble my ſelf to Argue with a Man that runs counter to all the Methods of Reaſoning.</p>
               <p>But bleſs me! were the drift of my Argument turned, and were I to prove the frequent Manifeſtations of Evil Spirits, what a number of Inſtances could I ſummon? The Prophet tells us of old, that <hi>Babylon</hi> was given up to become an Habitation for Evil Spirits: And can we think what he wrote was Allegorical only, when the Experience of our own Ages has ſhewn us what Power the Devil has ſometimes to infeſt even whole Cities and Countries?</p>
               <p>Thus, what ſhall we ſay to the Story related by Dr. <hi>More,</hi> of the Ghoſt of <hi>Contius,</hi> and others, that alone have diſturbed whole Cities, and driven almoſt Trade and Inhabitants from them? So, what ſhall we ſay to the Modern Relation of the <hi>Swedeland</hi> Witches, delivered us by Dr. <hi>Horneck,</hi> and atteſted as well by the King of <hi>Swedeland</hi> himſelf, as his Ambaſſadors, where Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of People, and whole Pariſhes almoſt, have been Convict of Witchcraft at a time; where the Devil often appeared in bodily ſhape in the Day-time, and the Power he had was ſo great, that almoſt the whole Kingdom was in a Terror at it.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65762:24"/>
               <p>I alledge theſe things becauſe done in our own Ages, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Thouſands of Witneſſes together; like the Apparitions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>Joſephus,</hi> before the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> Nor are they ſo ſingular neither, as ſome Men may pretend. What, was not the Story of the Devil of <hi>Maſcon</hi> (atteſted by the Famous Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>) notorious through the whole City? Was not the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance at <hi>Woodſtock</hi> ſuch, as not only laſted many days, but was to <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Commiſſioners (in whom the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nation was at that time.) And have not the Witchcrafts in <hi>New-England</hi> been ſuch of latter Years, that the very Governour, and Deputy-Governour there have thought it worth their whiles to atteſt them?</p>
               <p>I know theſe things rather illuſtrate the Power of the Devil than the Kingdom of God; but what of that, if theſe things are true, <hi>contraria luſtrant?</hi> And can we with any ſenſe imagine that there are inviſible Beings at every turn tempting Men to Evils, and yet their Vaſſals ſubject to our ordinary courſes of Juſtice; and not at the ſame time imagine that there are alſo holy inviſible Powers, who not only Rule the Malice of the wicked Spirits, but are as ready with their Graces to embrace the approaches of the good, as the Devils of the evil, were it not that our Wickedneſs with-held us from ſuch Bleſſings?</p>
               <p>But after all I know there are a ſort of <hi>Sadducees</hi> amongſt us, that neither theſe nor any other Arguments will be able to move: What is it to them, though that the Wiſdom of all Nations have made Laws againſt Wizards, and daily Execute them? What is it to them, though that <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Melancton,</hi> the firſt Reformers, have both atteſted ſuch Pranks of the Devil from their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and that the beſt of our Hiſtories brand many even of our Popes of being Conjurers and Wizards? The whole not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is a Chymera to them, and we poor <hi>Phariſaick</hi> Chriſtians, that believe ſuch things as Apparitions, Spirits, and a future ſtate, are a parcel of Credulous Fools with them, that deſerve not their Argument. But for my part, I can't think but that had theſe Men a Courage and Juſtice to Act impartially accordingly, they might deny the Truth of Chriſtianity, nay, and the very Exiſtence of the Deity its ſelf, with full as good a Reaſoning.</p>
               <p>Nor is the particular Miniſtry of Angels in theſe caſes altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be diſcern'd for our Evil and Deluſion only, as in Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts, but ſometimes for our Good and Aſſiſtance alſo: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65762:25"/>ſay, but the Holy Miniſters are generally more modeſt than the Apoſtate Spirits even when they do appear; beſides that our Wickedneſs drives them from us, or elſe ſurely we want no leſs certainty for the Proof of our Guardian Angels, beſides the general Inſtances before given, than our Evil Genius's, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are plain in this matter beyond doubt, and give us variety of Examples about it, beſides the particular words of Chriſt for it, That his little Ones have always their Angels in the preſence of God on their behalf.</p>
               <p>But alas! when one tells ſome Men of theſe things, or of the Angels that attended <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> ay, and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets, and Chriſt and his Apoſtles on oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, they tell you Scripture-times were not like other times, that theſe were ſingular Favours only: But what, can there be any ſenſe in ſuch ſhuffling? Shall the Scriptures otherwhere tell us expreſly how God has given his Angels charge over us, and that all theſe things are written for our Enſample? And ſhall we then againſt all Ingenuity continue to imagine that the firſt three Millenaries of the World ſhould be alone ſo ſingular in their Diſpenſations from the reſt?</p>
               <p>Beſides, what is more plain than that even in theſe latter days alſo we are not without the like Examples of the beſt Credit, of the aſſiſtances of Angels: Thus, is it not recorded (as I have wrote) particularly of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> how all the Plots of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were revealed to him by Dream and Viſion? And does not Hiſtory tell us, how <hi>Melancton</hi> and others have been often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from dangers through the notices of good Spirits? I may ſay, does not Judge <hi>Hales</hi> in his Contemplations aſſure us of the like Heavenly Notices to himſelf; and is there ſcarce either Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory or Book, that does not give us ſome or other like Inſtances about it?</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs 'tis but rare that we find that Familiarity from them, as is related of one — who is ſaid to be called up in the Morning by one, and to have had notice either of Company, or Books, if he entertained ſuch as the Angel was not pleaſed with. But the Genius of <hi>Socrates,</hi> of which he ſpeaks particularly him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Dying Orations, is what ſeems more familiar, and may be in the Experience of ſeveral others, had they made but a due and juſt Obſervation.</p>
               <p>He tells you, that at all times when he went about any thing that was evil or dangerous, he had certainly ſome private notice
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65762:25"/>of it, either by Dream, or otherwiſe; and in this reſpect, ſays he, I made it my conſtant Practice to obey my Monitor where I could: But, ſays he at preſent, though I hazard even my Life for the profeſſing of Truth, I find no check from him for the danger; and therefore, ſays he, I conclude, that as he that has been my Faithful Guide for theſe Threeſcore Years, knows bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what is good for me than my ſelf; he approves of my haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arding my ſelf for theſe greater Truths of God: And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect I can ſay my ſelf alſo, that ſcarce a conſiderable Action has ever happened in my Life, that I have not had by Dreams an apparent Prediction of it before hand, and ſometimes not without Advice.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot forbear the Recording of one more Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Providence that happened to an Acquaintance of mine, <hi>viz.</hi> That once being to take a Journey, in which he had an Election of two ways to go; in the Morning juſt before he aroſe, their appeared to him a Glorious Head, with an Hand pointing by it; it was ſeveral Years ſince, but if ever he was awake in his Life, he ſays it was when he ſaw this Apparition. I muſt confeſs, at firſt it had ſo conſiderable an impreſſion upon him, that he thought to wait on ſome Divines his Acquaintance near him for their Advice about it; but afterwards recollecting with himſelf, that he had a Diſpute which Road to go, and that Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Perſons had adviſed him to the Privated Road, he conſtrued the Divine Monition himſelf, as that it related to his Journey, and accordingly went that way he conceived pointed at; but what Deliverance he had by it God only knows, this he remembers, by obſerving it, he got very ſafely home to his Journey's end.</p>
               <p>And now ſince I have gone thus far, and as clearly and briefly as I have been able, led you through the ſtate of Prophecy to Tranſlation, and confirmed what I have ſaid, at leaſt I think ſufficiently by Examples; I think it may be high time,<note place="margin">Of Heaven.</note> after ſome little matter added concerning Heaven it ſelf; and ſome Directions for your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration towards this Kingdom, to draw towards a Concluſion: And in this caſe though the Rays and Joys of Heaven are too bright for Humane Underſtanding, yet there may be ſome Glympſe of it, that even our Natural Light may give us; ſo that though we cannot gaze far into the Bleſſed ſtate, ſurely that may not diſcourage us, but that we may trace it as far as it will lead us.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:65762:26"/>
               <p>When we remove to the Bleſſed Manſions above therefore, we muſt needs think withal that we ſhall change theſe our Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Corrupt Tabernacles, our Bodies there will be more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and void of Corruption; and our Senſations and Percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions not only new and different, but wonderfully more lively and vigorous than now, nay, and of an Eternal Duration; our Spirits there will never flag with Satiety and repetition of Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor ever be moved with Curioſity of change, but move on in a continued and wiſe Conſtancy in long and endleſs En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments.</p>
               <p>GOD himſelf at firſt, and as by a new Creation will then wipe away all Tears with their cauſes, and inſtead of them will Preſent us with an Unchangeable and Eternal Conſort of Joy, with Songs of his Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Mercy; we ſhall Pray without ceaſing, and Praiſe without tyring, and ſtand eternally enflamed and raviſhed with admiring the Glories, Beauties, yea, and Wonders of the Power, Juſtice, and Mercy of GOD.</p>
               <p>There no racking Curioſity for Wiſdom will torment us, we ſhall know, at leaſt as much as we ſhall ſee we ought to know: There no Tenderneſs for our Friends in this World will diſturb us, our Earthly Relations will vaniſh, we ſhall put them off with our Bodies; and they only will be regarded there by us as our Father and Brother, our Siſter and Mother, who have truly obeyed the Commands of our GOD, our only real Father.</p>
               <p>And to compleat all, GOD himſelf will place his Throne amongſt us, and though in reality he be every where, yet for our Comfort, he will make his moſt Glorious appearance amongſt us, whilſt Rings of Angels, and Principalities in Perfection, of Order and Addreſs, glorifie their great and wonderful Maker, even dazling them with his Glory from his Throne in the midſt of them. But O! what are the Miſeries that the Damned are to feel inſtead of this, for their Diſobedience and Wickedneſs?</p>
               <p>And what then, are theſe things thus? Nay, is there a GOD? And is not our Sabbath our one day in ſeven, that we beſtow on Religion,<note place="margin">Of Preparing our ſelves.</note> flung away in vain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us? Or is Religion really a ſerious Duty? If it is, let us learn to regard theſe things that are ſo evidently true, and that ſo nearly concern us in earneſt; and not like mean and baſe Hypocrites ſeem to regard them, when we really eſteem them to be but as a Jeſt or Tritle. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in earneſt begin to Purifie our ſelves, and prepare us for ſo great a Kingdom.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65762:26"/>
               <p>Let us walk always as in the ſight of GOD; let us avoid even all appearance of Evil, nay, and let us take care to work out our Salvations with Fear and Trembling, and not fall through a Preſumption of our own Strength, but rather truſt wholly on GOD. And laſtly, we muſt add to all this Sincerity; Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the only great and ſolid Foundation to build on, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member withal that we muſt actually endeavour through GOD's Grace to render our ſelves pure, and not barely expect GOD's Aſſiſtance, for that he never beſtows upon the ſluggiſh.</p>
               <p>Nor are or can be the Pangs of this New Birth, or Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration eaſie to a Worldly Mind; for as it muſt be entire, ſo we ought to be always ready, and that even preciſely, leſt the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom ſhould knock and ſurprize us at unawares: And hence alſo, even to keep all the Commandments from our Youth up is not enough, if we refuſe to ſell all, where the Glory of GOD requires it, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.62. we fall back from the Criſis that GOD is leading us to.</p>
               <p>And ſo alſo, as I have obſerved before, the ſelf-denyal, even of a common Martyrdom, is not enough; for the loweſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of theſe Glories here is required an entire reſignation, and without we are even born again, we cannot enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of GOD, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. And as many mens Luſts are dearer unto them than their Lives, ſo Life alone is not Sacrifice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to perfect a compleat new Birth.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> in Faith was forced to leave his Father's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try e're he had the Promiſe of another; and thus we ſee alſo, that we, with Chriſt, muſt learn to be able to deſpiſe this World, if ever we deſign for a better; and yet not, I ſay, neither that thou ſhouldſt tempt GOD in Health or Food, or ſell all to give to the Poor, till thou art called thereto.</p>
               <p>Further, if thou ſeekeſt this Kingdom in Curioſity, and not in Duty, and as a Servant of all, know GOD will never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thee in thy Luſts; and whereas if thou Addreſs him with an humble, conſtant, and diligent Application, thou wilt even wonder to ſee how GOD will purifie thee by degrees to Perfection.</p>
               <p>Take care therefore that thou be not like the Seed ſown in ſtony Ground, that will ſprout up faſt at firſt, but dye away in Affliction, for want of Root and Conſideration: So remember alſo, that Moderation is to be thy Fountain-Vertue, indeed the very Baſis ſupporting all. And withal take care that thou get Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65762:27"/>alſo, that thou mayeſt be the perfecter for the Service of GOD; if there be not Light in the Underſtanding, there cannot well be Heat in the Affections. And laſtly, to all theſe thou muſt add Patience; for as GOD hazards not our Tryals at a puſh, ſo we muſt expect to be made Perfect by Conſtancy, Patience, and Long-ſuffering.</p>
               <p>Or if you had rather, I ſhall preſcribe your Preparation in the Apoſtle's own words thus, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.16, 17. <hi>Rejoyce ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, pray without ceaſing, in every thing give thanks, for this is the will of GOD in Chriſt Jeſus concerning you. Quench not the Spirit, deſpiſe not Prophecyings, prove all things, hold faſt that which is good, abſtain from all appearance of evil.</hi> In truth, does not Chriſt reckon the Evil to his little Ones as to himſelf? <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.</p>
               <p>So in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Epiſtles, <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Ver.</hi> 6, 7, 8. <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble. Submit your ſelves therefore to GOD, reſiſt the Devil, and he will flee from you; draw nigh to GOD, and he will draw nigh to you. Cleanſe your hands, you ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and purifie your hearts, you double-minded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So alſo <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Finally, Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to encourage us, tells us from his Example, that we ſhould glory in our Infirmities, as GOD's Grace is ſufficient for us. So in <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. of the ſame Epiſtle, he tells us, that though we are troubled, we ought not to deſpair, that the Glory of GOD might ſhine the brighter in us as Earthen Veſſels; nor need we fear, for we have a moſt Solemn Promiſe, that we ſhall not be tempted beyond our ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Let us ſearch our ſelves therefore; like <hi>Achan,</hi> we all harbour the accurſed thing, and that it is that keeps us from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of GOD: Indeed were we entirely wicked, his Juſtice would not let us ſubſiſt; and as we are luke-warm, if in time we do not mend, we muſt expect him to ſpew us out.</p>
               <p>How long therefore ſhall we follow our dead Infidelity, and by our falſe Caſuiſm and Controverſies keep out the Kingdom of GOD from amongſt us? Did we, like the Noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> ſearch the Scriptures throughly, and not like little fooliſh Sects,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65762:27"/>take our Faith on truſt, and ſpend our time on Quarrels at Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, that ought to be employed in purifying our Lives and Practices. Did we hearken when GOD teaches us in our Conſciences, and ſtep into the Spiritual <hi>Betheſda,</hi> when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of GOD moves in our Meditations, 'twere impoſſible but that GOD ſhould lead us right.</p>
               <p>So, did we conſider alſo that our Sins and Impurities are as much in our Hearts and Eyes, as our Hands and Actions, we ſhould be more cautious of our Adulteries againſt the Law of GOD; but alas! we walk in blindneſs, and will not ſee; we waſte our Zeal in Controverſie, that ſhould be ſpent in true Piety; we caſt Miſts of Tradition and Church-Authority before us in diſtraction of our Brotherly Love; ſo that if we would, we can't ſee: In truth, were our Eye ſingle, we might hope for it; but alas, 'tis double, and our Luſts will not let us remove the Beam, and pluck out our right Eyes that offend us; we are too far enamoured with the Silver and Gold of the Whore, and the Luſts and Pride of Life, to be Diſciples of ſo great Reſignation.</p>
               <p>And what but this is it that forces God to afflict us to ſee? And what but this is it that makes us reform, and reform again? Becauſe our Corruptions fling us into our unaccountable Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and will not let us ſee the guilt of them. Alas! how can we, as St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, pretend to love our Heavenly Father, that we have not ſeen, when our Diſcords are ſo unreaſonable with our Brethren that we have ſeen? Surely if we ever intend to approach to God, we muſt learn to lay a deeper Foundation in our mutual Love and Charity towards it.</p>
               <p>Further, in ſeeking this Kingdom alſo we muſt learn to avoid Idleneſs as bane, and ſeek heartily for Wiſdom: Spare not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to riſe early, and to be up late for it. Nor muſt you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the leaſt prejudice in your Wiſdom, wilful Error and Piety can never ſubſiſt together; and yet remember withal, that 'tis not your large Bodies of Divinity ſo much, as 'tis GOD muſt lead you, not I mean, that you ſhould tempt GOD neither for that Knowledge which Induſtry ought to attain; but that you ought to Pray and Meditate as well as Study, and hearken as well to the ſincere checks of thy Conſcience as Notions of Books, nor ſlight this Advice; for know GOD thus firſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates thoſe Souls that he intends to inhabit.</p>
               <p>And yet let not this diligent Sincerity run thee into Care nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but truſt wholly on GOD without Anxiety after thy beſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65762:28"/>Endeavours, and yet be ſtill on thy Guard, and ever aiming at the higheſt pitch of Sincerity and Purity; indeed forfeit not thine Integrity though but even in a Trifle, for how doſt thou know, O Man, but that that may be thy fatal Tryal?</p>
               <p>And to crown all this, add the Charity of a courageable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Mankind; fear not the face of Man, but rebuke him throughly, and reſcue the Honour of GOD from his Errors; and yet not that I would have thee diſturb Men by thy Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or caſt Pearls before Swine, or go about to Preach, as Chriſt did, till ſent; but I would have thee to ſeek all Prudent Occaſions to Adviſe thy Brother, to reſcue the Honour of GOD, advance his Kingdom, and ſave the Soul of thy Brother if it offers.</p>
               <p>And if thou doſt thus, thou needeſt not fear thy Succeſs; for if Chriſt could tell the Scribe for his diſcreet Anſwer, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.34. <hi>that he was not far from the Kingdom of GOD,</hi> thou, if thou hazardeſt thus all for his Glory, needeſt not doubt it ſurely; but elſe if thou forſake not all, thou canſt not be his Diſciple, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.33. As our Saviour ſays, <hi>The Children of this World are wiſer than the Children of Light,</hi> Luke 16.8. Or elſe they could never be miſtaken ſo much in their Methods to Salvation as they are.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, GOD requires a Self-denyal in this beyond a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paſſionate ſpurt, I mean a real and continual one; but what then, dare we not truſt him? And has he not aſſured us of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and that we ſhall not loſe by it, even in this World, and that though we fail in the Attempt? And what remains then, but that we believe either that he can't help us, or is not Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? Now, to ſay, he can't help us, is manifeſtly a Lye, for even the Coeleſtial Orbs, bigger than the Earth, move at this inſtant by his Providence; much more then can be move a little Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or do any leſs Act to ſave us. And wilt thou charge him with being unfaithful? Pray tell me then whom it is that he has deceived; if thou canſt not, doſt not thou calumniate him?</p>
               <p>What then remains, but that you think 'tis not poſſible for a Man to purifie himſelf to that degree that I preſcribe? But as to that, I ſay, 'tis falſe, he may; no Man, I believe, can purifie himſelf from Frailties, for they are Humane; but from wilful Guilts of all kinds they may, or elſe GOD is unjuſt to require it, and which I am ſure he is not; if ſo, therefore provided we
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65762:28"/>are wary againſt all wilful Omiſſions or Commiſſions, we need not fear the injury of Frailties.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Ver.</hi> 17, 18. That <hi>Elias was a man ſubject to like Paſſions as we are, and he prayed earneſtly that it might not rain, and it rained not on the Earth for the ſpace of three Years and ſix Months: And he prayed again, and the Heavens gave rain, and the Earth brought forth her fruit.</hi> And indeed it was the ſame <hi>Elias</hi> that was afterwards tranſlated.</p>
               <p>If this Power were given to <hi>Elias</hi> therefore, who had not the advantages of Chriſtianity to help him, where lyes any juſt grounds for our doubt of it? You will ſay, ſometimes in doubts you are forced to diſſatisfie your Conſcience where you know not how to reſolve it: But as to that, as I have before directed thee, when with thy ſincereſt Judgment thou haſt choſen the good, reſolve and ſink not into ſcruple, but rather rejoyce in thy Reſolution, and that thou art ſure that if after thine hearty Induſtry thou erreſt, that even GOD himſelf will reveal it to thee, rather than thine Error ſhould injure thee, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. or elſe indeed, as the Apoſtle hath ſaid, 'tis damnable.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, therefore learn to be even obſtinately conſtant in thy Devotions, and remember to do all things for the Glory and Honour of GOD; even to eat, drink, and be merry, without Faith, is Sin: For who gives us theſe Bleſſings? Is not that worth our care? Much more therefore when we ſeek our own Glory GOD may juſtly Sacrifice us in our beſt Actions. So never act in doubt, to ſtifle Doubts, is to quench GOD's Spirit; and no Man can ever be ſaid to walk with GOD, as <hi>Enoch</hi> was ſaid to do, to be tranſlated, and yet reſiſt him.</p>
               <p>But for the better purifying your ſelf, I ſhall now explain a little the Nature of the Grace of GOD, to ſhew you how it leads you,<note place="margin">Of Grace.</note> and how you ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
               <p>Know then, that whatever may ſeem to us, to GOD there is no Accident, but he tries us in all things; thus, there is not an Example or Meditation that he will not make us Anſwer for as Talents; nay, whatever our Conſcience recommends to us, whether by Reading, Hearing, or Recollection, tis all one; he will charge it all to Account againſt us, as well as the Grace that he imparts to us by a more immediate Revelation.</p>
               <p>Nay, and even in Revelations, think you that <hi>Socrates</hi> was not a Prophet as well as <hi>Micha?</hi> If his Order and Diſpenſation
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65762:29"/>was not ſo Glorious, yet his Divine Aſſiſtance was as juſt in its degree. And this we may aſſuredly learn further, that he that with <hi>Socrates</hi> will not cheriſh the beginnings of Grace, and take it in every Opportunity that it offers it ſelf, ſhall never be able to improve himſelf in it, or to grow in it to the perfection of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>How wonderful, may I ſay therefore, are GOD's Methods in bringing his Sons to Glory? I might add, did not our Darling Luſts ungratefully blind us, we ſhould be even raviſhed with GOD's Wiſdom; but our Eyes are groſs, and we have no Faith to ſee thoſe ordinary Graces of GOD; indeed the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ones of Viſions, Miracles, and Tongues, we admire, but will not hazard an extraordinary Tryal to attain them.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, 'tis the ſame Grace that gave us our Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy of old, and our Divinity of late, as I have ſaid; the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation now indeed is more glorious, but the Spirit is the ſame, nor indeed in this his more glorious Diſpenſation are his Gifts always the ſame; 'tis plain from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. that the Apoſtles had not all the ſame Powers; one had Prophecy, another had Tongues, and a third Miracles; and no one was compleat in Grace but Chriſt Jeſus only: And yet even in this Imperfection the variety became a Beauty in the Church, and the ſeveral different Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers yet made a Body uniform and compleat.</p>
               <p>But as for the meaner Diſpenſations of Grace, they are infinite; thus the gentle, GOD moves through Advice, the Obſtinate, through Afflictions; ſome, like <hi>Job,</hi> he purifies by Miſeries, others, like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> he hardens by his Rod; and thus ſometimes he puniſhes the Wicked for Example, ſometimes he ſuffers the Righteous to have his Judgments for a blind, ſometimes he raiſes the Wicked as a Scourge to the Luke-warm, and ſometimes he flatters them in their Proſperity, ſo ſometimes he takes away the Righteous in Curſe to the Wicked; and all this doth one and the ſame Spirit, actuated by a variety ſuitable to the Wiſdom of GOD, and only to be diſcerned by an Eye of Purity and Faith.</p>
               <p>Now our Reflections in this matter are theſe: Firſt, That though GOD thus gradually haſtens our Tryal, yet withal he has promiſed us, <hi>That all things ſhall work together for the beſt for them that fear him,</hi> Rom. 8.28. Our uſe of them is, that we learn and follow our Duty to GOD by his firſt and gentle means of Grace, not only that his Grace may the more freely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65762:29"/>work on us, but that we may avoid his Rod to force us; and as it is eaſier to kill a Lion's Whelp than a Lion, and to root up a young Oak than an old one; ſo in ſins alſo, the firſt act is eaſily hindred, but we may bear the laſh of many an heavy Affliction e're we are cured of an Habit.</p>
               <p>But beſides GOD's Grace, and our own Endeavours, we muſt add Prayers likewiſe, if ever we intend for a real Purity and the Kingdom of GOD; not,<note place="margin">Of Prayer.</note> I mean, that we ſhould think proudly through Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to Storm GOD's Throne by it neither; but we ought with an humble Application to Pray without ceaſing, and as the Scriptures tell us, that the Kingdom of GOD comes not with Obſervation, and we cannot know its time though we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured it will come; ſo not only in Prayers, but Purity we ought not to be backwards whenever the Heavenly Spirit ſhall ſee good to viſit us.</p>
               <p>Remember thy Victory is through Prayer, and not through Study only; not that we ſhould neglect the Study of Wiſdom neither, and beſides that Prayer through Importunity will make a real change in our Lives; for as we know, to Pray in our ſins, or for a thing unlawful, is vain; ſo by our conſtant Prayer we ſhall do a double Duty, and force our ſelves into Purity, as well as obtain the Bleſſings we deſire.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the Kingdom of Heaven is as Journey of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſteps in Faith, and therefore we muſt allow ſo many Prayers at leaſt to our Importunity; for believe me, if you faint at the firſt Tenth or Hundredth asking, you will never attain it; ſo that though thy Prayers obtain not immediately, neither faint, nor expoſtulate arrogantly with GOD, but humbly know thy fault, and pray his Mercy, and his Will be done; nor deſpair ever, for Faith has good grounds, and has overcome; ſtudy therefore to purifie thy ſelf for ever on, and then by thy Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity thou muſt prevail, and GOD will cleanſe thee for thy Conſtancy and Sincerity's ſake; for though no Man can merit before him, yet he has promiſed to Reward every Man according to his Works.</p>
               <p>Remember alſo that GOD hates Paſſion, the Sacrifice of Fools; and as he has given thee good grounds for Faith, ſo thou muſt allow for Importunity, for even Chriſt was forced to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him with Tears, and <hi>Moſes</hi> to hold up his Hands all day, if he would that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould prevail; And beſides,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65762:30"/>if thou art not anſwered in thy Prayers, may be thou wilt ſee ſome Reaſon and Corruption, if thou waiteſt with Patience, why thou art not; and if not, thou ſeeſt that thou haſt this new Leſſon to learn, that thou art to Conquer through long and humble begging, and not as if you intended to Command GOD. Was not even Chriſt himſelf forced to wait, like <hi>Jonas</hi> in the Whale's Belly, till his time was come?</p>
               <p>In this therefore Pray to GOD himſelf to direct you, as <hi>Moſes, Samuel,</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets have done before you: GOD will not be rob'd of his Glory, and therefore if thou wilt not act purely in reſignation to his Grace, thou mayſt be loſt a thouſand times e're thou arrive at Glory; are you ſure you Pray right, when you do not add withal, <hi>Thy Will be done?</hi> Pray rather therefore that thou mayſt be curſed in this World, to be happy in the next, and ſeek wholly for the Glory of GOD, and to be reſigned to his Will; nor be impatient, remember <hi>Moſes</hi> was forced to wait after that he had fled for deſigning to be a deliverer.</p>
               <p>But for Example, I have added hereunto a Form of Prayer to be uſed by thoſe that ſhall ſee convenient.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Dear Father,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <hi>THough through the dint of Paſſion and fiery Zeal I cannot prevail with thee to enter thy Kingdom, yet I do not doubt but that I ſhall be able to do it through Conſtancy and Importunity, unleſs I am wanting to my ſelf, for ſo thou haſt promiſed me through my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; pardon me therefore, if (with the moſt entire ſubmiſſion to thy Will) I continually wreſtle with the in Prayer; O GOD, I would not preſumptuouſly offer at thy Kingdom thus by force, were it not that thou haſt given me encouragement; but now thou haſt, I beg thee, for thine own Glory, for thy Mercy's ſake, and for the good of thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thou wouldeſt not leave thy poor Churches deſtitute, but confound the works of Satan, and teach us the way to thy Kingdom; and even now, O Lord, I approach thee in all Humility, and after all my Petitions, thy Will only be done. Nothing that is preſumptuous, wicked, or proud, can find acceptance in thy ſight, and therefore I dare not move a ſtep beyond what thy Precepts give me Authority; grant me therefore that as I purſue thine own Sacred Dictates and Commands, ſo I may prevail with thee, and not let thee go, until, like</hi> Jacob, <hi>I have got a Bleſſing from thee; I mean, not a Temporal one, but the Eternal one of thy Kingdom, through Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>Amen.</closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65762:30"/>
               <p>Or if this offend you, or ſeem imperfect, uſe that great and general Catholicon preſcribed by our Saviour himſelf, and which indeed is ſo general, that it ſuits with all Men, of all Religions and Profeſſions whatever, and is withal ſo perfect, that I might add, the Wit of Man is not able to exceed it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">When we Pray, we ought to do it for others as well as our ſelves.</note> 
                  <hi>Father, which art in</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Our Addreſſes to God are to the chief. Seat of his Divine Majeſty.</note> 
                  <hi>Heaven. Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy Name. Thy</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Note, the three firſt Petitions in this Prayer are for the Honour of GOD, and which we ought to learn to ſeek before all things.</note> 
                  <hi>Kingdom</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">That is, to the deſtruction of Satans,</note> 
                  <hi>come. Thy Will be done in Earth, as it is in</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">ſurely then poſſible</note> 
                  <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Give us this day our daily bread,</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">all outward Neceſſaries.</note> 
                  <hi>and forgive us our Treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us.</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">GOD will Judge us as we do others; let us beware therefore what we do in this caſe, leſt we Pray in vain.</note> 
                  <hi>And lead us not into Temptation, but deliver us from evil,</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Theſe laſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions are for our ſelves purely, and therefore moſt deſervedly follow the other.</note> 
                  <hi>for thine is the Kingdom, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">This Doxology is as well to ſtir up our Faith at laſt, as to Praiſe GOD.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Glory, for ever, and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>To this I ſhall alſo add four Rules whereby the Scriptures tell us that we ſhall be accepted in our Prayers.<note n="*" place="margin">The Author for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon deſires all his Readers par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Prayers for him, either if he is in the Truth, to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and continue him in it, or if he is in an Error, to let him be taught, and given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand better, even ſo I beſeech thee, O Lord, for Chriſt's ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </note> The Firſt, when we Pray for one another; thus St. <hi>Peter</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of Priſon by an Angel. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in Chriſt's Name to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Publick Communion. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Pray without ceaſing, remembring neither to ask amiſs, nor in your Luſts, <hi>James</hi> 4.3. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. Fourthly, To Pray every day afreſh, and as GOD's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall by your Conſcience lead you, remembring that GOD is to be worſhipped in Spirit and Truth.</p>
               <p>Now, though the ſtate and corruption of the Church may Excuſe us in our Duty in the Second of theſe, to wit, as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Communion; yet as to the other three, nothing can
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65762:31"/>excuſe us, and if poſſible nothing ought to excuſe us even from the Second alſo; indeed if we either wilfully or negligently diſregard theſe Rules, we need not wonder if our Prayers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prevail.</p>
               <p>☞ Note, By Old Tradition the World as it has laſted 2000 Years before the Law, and 2000 Years after it, ſo alſo is it to laſt 2000 Years after the Coming of Chriſt, e're we arrive at the great and final <hi>Millerium,</hi> or Sabbath. But a ſurer Rule is, that GOD hath put the Times and Seaſons of all things in his own Power, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I have hereunto added alſo a Copy of an Extraordinary Dream that I had ſome Years ſince, which I recollected I had a Copy of by me ſome time after I wrote this Treatiſe, and which ſeeming to tend ſo directly to the ſame purpoſe, I thought I could not well at the ſame time deny the Reader a ſight of it together herewith. What is the true meaning and purport of it, God, who only knows, will ſhew in his own time; in the mean while I have delivered it down very near in very ſame rude form of Expreſſion that I wrote it ſeveral Years ſince.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Memorandum,</hi> That about the latter end of <hi>May,</hi> in the Year 1681. juſt upon my Recovery from the Small-Pox, I had the Strange and Remarkable Dream following; and which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Notable in its intent and coherence, as it was lively in my reception of it, about two Years after, and whilſt every Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of it remained clear in my Memory, I wrote it down (ſome little Additions by preſent Memory excepted) as enſueth.</p>
               <p>I imagined my ſelf Travelling, I thought, to <hi>France,</hi> and it ſeemed as it were by a Chariot, or Engine of Ropes, and by which I ſeemed firſt to be raiſed up to a very great height, and afterwards to be ſlid down again forwards with it, as with a very great ſwiftneſs.</p>
               <p>Methoughts my Journey was by Moon-ſhine, and whilſt I was thus raiſed in the Air, I imagined I more perfectly ſurvey'd the Heavens than now, and they appeared to me but as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed wooden Engine, however of a vaſtly large Architecture, and the Moon ſhining brightly in them. Methoughts alſo I ſaw the reſt of the World almoſt all mudling below, except ſome
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65762:31"/>few, and who ſeemed in the like little Chariots beneath me.</p>
               <p>At length as I travelled on, I apprehended I had a pretty little Book given me, what it was, I cannot declare, but this I remember, I peruſed it with a very great Satisfaction, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued it in my hand for ſome time, till by and by I was diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the preſence of a Guardian Angel; I apprehended he ſate on my Chariot by me on my Right Hand as it were behind me: At firſt indeed he ſhewed himſelf but dimly to my ſight, but even his Preſence ſo ſeemed to inſpire me with an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Devotion.</p>
               <p>But at laſt methoughts he became familiar and viſible, even as a Friend to me, and then talking with him of ſeveral mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I remember I asked him, though 'twas with indifference, whether 'twere God's Will I ſhould ever attain conſiderable Riches? Upon this he puts his Hand (as if a Man) into his Pocket, and ſeeming to pull out parings of Gold, thence he puts them into his Hat, where they jingling like Gold on his handling them, I imagined by an extraordinary Power he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately alſo melted them with his Hand, and framed them into Coin and Medals, and then begun to tell me, how 'twas God's Will, that I ſhould not have it all my ſelf, but that a part of it muſt go for Charitable Uſes.</p>
               <p>And now when it ſeemed all coined, and I expected imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to receive it, ſtraight the Devil appears, and would needs have taken it from him; he could not indeed, but I imagined I could never receive it upon it, however ſeeing this Attempt in vain, he deſigns a ſecond, and turning about upon me, thought to aſſault me to prejudice me too, but that the Angel defended me; but now, what with Devotion, and the ſenſe of my Angel's aid together, methoughts I begun to increaſe my Courage.</p>
               <p>However he aſſaults me again in the ſhape of a tall Woman, and I thought he would have prejudiced me too, but that now I imagined my ſelf grown much ſtronger, and yet ſtill the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel was forced to help me, and drive her away; but this I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly remember, that in his ſhape as a Man before, he did not ſeem half ſo furious as now, and when in the ſhape of a Woman.</p>
               <p>So I could obſerve this further too, that I did not riſe ſo high now, nor fall ſo low as I did before; indeed my Journey in my Chariot now ſeemed very near the Earth, and for the moſt part
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65762:32"/>keeping a continual diſtance from it, whereas at the beginning ſometimes I ſhot as almoſt from the Clouds up and down.</p>
               <p>But now a further Misfortune befalls me, and my Angel tells me, he muſt leave me; he tells me, he muſt go and aſſiſt the afflicted, and who, as he ſaid, were ſpoiled by Robbers. I muſt confeſs I could not but be troubled at the hearing of the loſs that I was like to have, but withal methoughts I willingly and devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly parted with my Company, when I ſaw 'twas on ſo good an Occaſion.</p>
               <p>And now methinks he forſakes me, and all my Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the noiſe of diſmal and terrible groans as I imagined coming from Men that ſeemed robbed and wounded; however this hindred not but that I continued on in my Chariot, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughts now inſtead of my Angel, I ſeemed to have three or four of my Earthly Friends about me, though I cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in particular who they were.</p>
               <p>But methoughts their Company at this Juncture was of very great ſatisfaction to me, for I loved them entirely, and ſo that now I ſeemed near as happy as ever: However for all this we are not even yet free from our Old Enemy the Devil, who now taking the advantage of the Angel's abſence, endeavours to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault us afreſh.</p>
               <p>But now methoughts my Strength and Courage is increaſed much beyond what it was, and I vanquiſhed him alone, and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Company from him too, and who ſeemed to truſt to me, and whom he aſſaulted as my Friends; ſo that now ſeeing he could do me no hurt by force, he falls to reproaches and hiſſing; his reproach, I remember, was, <hi>You Jew, You Jew,</hi> which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated twice or thrice, and then went away hiſſing.</p>
               <p>But this was ſo far from diſmaying me, that it rather cheared and encouraged me; and now whilſt I am full of Devotion and Thankſgiving for my Deliverance, methinks in the midſt of it, to mine inexpreſſible Joy, a Dove in Glory, as I conceived the Holy Ghoſt, deſcended on me; and now I am almoſt ſwallowed up in Joy, and raviſhed with Ecſtaſies and Raptures; nay, and more, after this I am no more troubled by my Enemy the Devil; but as he aſſaulted me this laſt time, and as indeed he did at every other time, at the left ſide of my Chariot, ſo now going under the Chariot from me to the right, I heard him howl grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly (ſeeming as at near a Furlong off) on his Departure, to cry, <hi>O my Heel! O my Heel!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65762:32"/>
               <p>But now my Devotion ſeems to move me another way, and now I reſolve to go and do the ſame good Work that my Angel was gone about before me, methinks accordingly I leave my Friends, and leave my Chariot, and jump immediately on the Earth, and where I imagine I go forth with Vigour: The place I enter ſeems a Wood or Wilderneſs, and where I heard moſt lamentable Cries; but at laſt coming to the Robbers, though I fight heartily and bravely with them, yet methinks they are too hard for me, and I am ſhot Arms and Legs to the ſtumps, and impriſoned by them.</p>
               <p>However all this doth not happen to me neither without the Comfort of abundance of good Friends, for now I imagine I have hundreds about me, and all endeavouring to chear me in my Misfortune, but alas, all to no purpoſe; for now methinks by a ſecret Voice by God I am ſtruck into a deep deſpair for ſome Preſumption I have committed, and now I am all in Priſon and Tears, I can neither ſleep nor reſt, continually Repenting, and yet comfortleſs, till at laſt another Voice, as from God, aſſures me of Forgiveneſs, and now I can enjoy my Friends again.</p>
               <p>Nay, and in a little time I am reſtored to my Limbs, and freed from Priſon again, and now I enter a ſecond Chariot, and here my Chariot was as before, only that it ſeemed to carry me even, and without either riſes or falls as the other did; nor had I in this Chariot the leaſt Company, either of Man or Spirit in view by the way, but methoughts I continued on quietly by my ſelf, till at laſt methoughts my Journey ended, by my Chariot's ſtopping of its ſelf, and ſhooting its ſelf againſt the Earth, juſt as a Ship does againſt the ſhore.</p>
               <p>Here therefore I am forced to alight, but I am no ſooner got up, but ſtraight I find a two-edged or bladed Sword in my hand; here alſo methoughts I immediately met a true Friend, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truly faithful and cordial to me, methinks we fight the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers again, or ſome other Enemy, and here methinks my Sword does extraordinary Execution, and I fight till I diſſolve, as if I vaniſhed both Body and Sword into Spirit.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:65762:33"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX OF <hi>Two Diſcourſes:</hi> THE I. <hi>Of</hi> PERSECUTION, <hi>declaring the law of Nations in Matters of Religion.</hi> THE II. <hi>Of</hi> CATHOLICK COMMUNION, <hi>or the Neglected Duty of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Law of Nations in Religion.</head>
               <p>IN Religion, both they that plead for Perſecution, and they that are for an Abſolute Toleration, are equally in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams; the mean therefore muſt be evident, to wit, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Eſtabliſhment between both; and which that I may the better ſet forth, I ſhall firſt take care briefly to refute all colour for Perſecution. Secondly, As clearly as I can I ſhall ſhew the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65762:33"/>Miſchiefs of an Abſolute Toleration. And laſtly, I hope as evidently to deſcribe the more Excellent Mean in a moderate Eſtabliſhment. I begin with the firſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is not my Deſign, whilſt I write againſt Perſecution, thereby to make any Apology for Religious Villanies; no, an Error in Religion ought to be ſcratch'd by our Pens, but an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral Member, no doubt, like a Gangreen, ought to be cut off; <hi>Et ne pars ſincera trahatur,</hi> let no Man therefore here unjuſtly charge me, that whilſt I make Apology for the Conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Peace of States, I withal ſeem to Plead for ſuch Religious Villanies, as are not fit to be ſuffered.</p>
               <p>But for a Peaceable Profeſſion of Religion, be it what it will, I would fain ask this Queſtion, Why ſhould Men be perſecuted from it? If you force them by Argument from their Belief, well and good; but if by Power and Might only, either you make them Libertines, if you leave them to uſe no Religion, or damn them for Hypocrites, if you force them to a Falth againſt their Conſciences.</p>
               <p>But no, you'll force Men to believe by it, you ſay; bleſs me, that Men can be ſo abſurd! as if Senſe were to be confounded by Power, or Truth to be altered by Might. What ſhall I ſay? To force Men to believe againſt their Conviction of Truth, is impoſſible; force them to lye and diſſemble indeed we may, if there be any Merit in that; and who can doubt but that when Mens Conſciences are tumbled from Pillar to Poſt at every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of State, as is too often done, but that ſuch is the effect of it?</p>
               <p>But no, ſays the <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> you miſtake, our Religion conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues one, and changes not; ay, and by that means they take as excellent a courſe to make their growing Errors as eternal as their Reformation impoſſible; and yet can even all that hinder, but that a Proteſtant State provailing on them, may uſe them full as ſcurvily as they uſe others; and why not juſtly too, ſince but with the ſame falſe Preſumption that they meaſured to others before?</p>
               <p>But bleſs me! be it ſo or not, is not this very agreeable in the mean while to the true Chriſtian Genius? Surely this is an admirable way of helping weaker Brethren, as that preſcribes to enſnare them thus to their Ruines; nay, and what? when we perverſely and wickedly thus force Men to come to our Church, though againſt their Conſciences, can we pretend that we act
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65762:34"/>any thing like what was deſigned in the Goſpel, which purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly orders all ſuch Profane Perſons to be avoided.</p>
               <p>Beſides, what do we do in this, but take the ſureſt way to make the good and ſincere Men of all ſides only ſuffer, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed who alone ought to be ſpared? Alas! our Atheiſts and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites they know well enough how to dance after the Pipes of the Times, be your Teſts and Enforcements what they will: But I'le maintain, let a State but change her eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for twice or thrice together, and give each Party on the change a power of Perſecution, they ſhall more effectually root out all their Honeſt Men, than by all the cunningeſt Policies in the World beſides.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, As for an Abſolute Toleration, 'tis ſuch a ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and inſipid Project of Imagination, that never any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Body of Men ſince the Creation entertained it; when Men can love all Religions alike, or, which is all one, hate them all, ſuch a Chymera may paſs Muſter with them: Or elſe to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that Men can encourage the true and falſe Religions alike, has as much ſenſe in it as they have Zeal for the Faith, that can do it.</p>
               <p>Thus even the Primitive Chriſtians that could complain very much of the Pagans Perſecuting them in <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s time, yet even they themſelves, under <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> would not ſuffer the Heathens to Sacrifice to their Goddeſs Fortune. And thus thoſe very Proteſtants in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> days, that could complain ſo juſtly of Martyrdom, and Fire and Faggot, yet could not forbear afterwards ſome Pecuniary Mulcts on Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters themſelves.</p>
               <p>So alſo thoſe Diſſenters that in the Reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, could complain ſo furiouſly of the High-Commiſſion Court, yet when by the War in 1640. they could get the Church of <hi>England</hi> under, ſtraight they could treat her much worſe; and yet when they fell under the Laſh again in 1660. though they were treated lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle worſe than they deſerved, and met with leſs Severity than they formerly exerciſed, yet could they complain as furiouſly as before. And pray, ſince the late Revolution, when the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians in <hi>Scotland</hi> got the Epiſcopals under, have they not trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them with Rigour enough?</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, to tell them that are able to ſuppreſs the oppoſite Party, that they ought to be contented with an equal Toleration,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65762:34"/>is Nonſenſe, and will never be regarded, at leaſt it never was yet. And ſo to tell them that are in Poſſeſſion, that they ought to bear with a riſing Sect or Opinion, though it may hereafter endanger them, is of the ſame Nature. I may ſay, offer this Argument to the Pagan, Jew, Mahumetan, to the Catholick, Arrian, Presbyterian, or Independant, where they are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and ſee if they will admit it.</p>
               <p>In plain terms, there is no Party that is ſincere in their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but what will endeavour to propagate it by all fair ways, and 'tis well if ſome won't endeavour by fair and foul too to get their Religion to have the Preheminence. 'Tis plain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that as Heart-burnings, Jealouſies, and Animoſities, ay, and at laſt, open Seditions and Rebellions, muſt needs grow from ſuch a Rivalry ſtate of Religion, and as is proved by every day's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, ſo the State of Neceſſity, and for Peace ſake alſo, will be bound to ſet up but one, and that the chief Religion in their Judgments only, and to depreſs and diſencourage the reſt by moderate Penalties; and which brings me to the third and laſt thing propoſed, to wit, an Enquiry into that Golden Mean of a rightfully eſtabliſhed Church, between a Bloody Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a Lawleſs and Libertine Toleration.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, Our buſineſs that remains therefore is to examine fully and freely into the true and real bounds of an Eſtabliſhed or National Church; and which that I may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do, I ſhall firſt trace Perſecution from her Fountain by the hand, and after that conducting her to that moderate pitch which ſuch an eſtabliſhed Church ſhall require; leave her there as to a Standard of Truth for all the Churches and States in the World to follow. <hi>Juſtum eſt quod aequè mihi &amp; tibi convenit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to begin, Who is it we ſhall Arraign for Perſecution?</p>
               <p>Firſt, Charge the State, ſhe'll tell you, that 'tis the Church that ſets her on, and enforces it as neceſſary with her.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Charge the Church, ſays even <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf, we do but Excommunicate Men, and if the State afterwards, who finds Hereticks and Schiſmaticks as bad as Traytors, puniſhes them accordingly, can we help it?</p>
               <p>Very well, the caſe is plain then, the Prieſt will never be a Butcher himſelf, ſo long as he can get the Magiſtrate to do his Drudgery; pray God, on the other ſide, the Magiſtrate learn ſo much Wit, as not to be Butcher and Villain too, to ſerve him.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65762:35"/>
               <p>Beſides, in this we have gained another point too, in ſeeing how plainly the Churches have all renounced Perſecution; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus far, I may ſay, we are clear the Power is in the State, or no where; therefore there we will fix, and there alone we will endeavour to bound it.</p>
               <p>To begin therefore, to ſay, that the State has no Right to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in Religion, is as falſe as to ſay, that they may Perſecute illimitably, if Peace be the care of the State, and Religion ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported or abuſed, tends to the advance or detriment of the Peace, 'tis plain Religion's as great an Object of the State's care as any thing.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, I might ſhew how <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and all the other Holy Men of Old declared this Obligation upon them as Magiſtrates; but as at preſent I ſhall rather Argue from a Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>max of Fundamental Reaſon of State, than bare Scripture-Proof, ſo I ſhall paſs ſuch Topicks by.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Propoſitions for the Neceſſity of Religion in States.</head>
               <p n="1">1. States are all Contracts, as all Contracts therefore depend Originally upon Religion, having no other Obligations; ſo 'tis plain that no State can have any other Baſis than Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this is ſo irriſiſtible a Reaſon for the State's care of Religion, that one may add, that even Rebellion does not more ruin the Walls, than Irreligion the Foundation of States.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That it will alſo follow from hence, and as is indeed every day atteſted by Experience, not only that the more united the Religion of the State, the ſurer alſo muſt the State be, but that the better the Religion, the happier the State alſo; in truth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion's the very Cement of States, and if that be naught, all's naught.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, Hence alſo it muſt follow, not only that a looſe and abſolute Toleration muſt be odious both to God and Man, but that the more divided the Religion in a State is, the weaker the State is; and that ſuch States are naturally Self-murderers as do not take care to encourage any Religion at all.</p>
               <p>The two Conſequences therefore that follow from hence, are,</p>
               <p n="1">1st, That every State is bound, rather than fail, by a moderate force to encourage ſome Religion or other, and if poſſibly, the beſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, And that for the ſame Reaſon alſo they are as much bound to puniſh all manner of Atheiſm, Irreligion, and Libertiniſm, as any other Crimes whatever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65762:35"/>
               <head>Propoſitions for the Neceſſity of one National Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1. As the Unity of Truth cannot let Magiſtrates love all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions alike, ſo the Eſtabliſhed Religion can be but one, and that both in Conſcience and Intereſt too; ſince but to think of ſetling more, were equally unſincere and vain to their purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That all States have this Power alike, and conſequently may juſtly preſume their Churches and Faiths to be right, when ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely choſen by them, and conſequently that all Subjects are bound, in Conſcience at leaſt, to aſſent in Peace to ſuch Choice, if not Worſhip, for fear of worſe conſequences, and as the leſs ought to bear with and be ruled by the greater.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That all Men on the ſame Account may be juſtly required to contribute to the Religion of the State as much as any other Tax, and that be it what it will, ſince 'tis for the ſupport of Religion in general, and not the particular Sect that they are bound to it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That Hereticks and Schiſmaticks for the ſame Reaſon may be juſtly kept under by moderate Penalties, both as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Religion and deſtroy its Unity, and conſequently in the end the State together with it; and on this Account the Church and State are both bound in Conſcience mutually to preſerve and help each other.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That ſuch alſo may be moſt juſtly debar'd from all manner of Power and Office in the State, and that if occaſion, with the ſevereſt Penalties, leſt by their mutual Jarrings, they not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Peace of the Church, but the State together with it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That though many have cryed up an abſolute Toleration of all Religions in contradiction of this, yet, as has been often and plainly experienced, it has been rather that they deſigned to wreſt the Power for themſelves, or that they have not cared for any Religion, and ſo endeavoured to confound all, than that they could pretend any Senſe or Conſcience for it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, That therefore this ſeems but as a moderate and juſt mean betwixt the Tyranny of afflicting Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences on the one ſide, and the looſeneſs of a Barbarous and Irreligious State of the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rules for the Puniſhment of Irreligion, and Religious Offences.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That for the ſame Reaſon the State is bound to take care of Religion; Atheiſts and Libertines require immediate Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65762:36"/>as Men Outlawing themſelves, and in truth I little doubt but that, did not their petty numbers and ſhifts protect them rather than their merits, they would find themſelves generally ſerved but little better.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he that openly Blaſphemes God, be treated as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt; and he that publickly profeſſes no Religion, as a Libertine.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That violent Hereticks and Schiſmaticks be puniſhed as Men that are Seditious, and Railing Controverters as Libellers without Religion ſhould Apologize for the Diſturbances they hazard, and which it ſhould rather aggravate for the Abuſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That if Men hold Dominion to be founded in Grace, that that is to dethrone the State by Principle, and that ſuch Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Pity juſt as much as High-way Men, that Rob out of Conſcience, and becauſe that they think that all things ought to be in Common.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That Jeſuits and Emiſſaries, who transfer the Supremacy, by the ſame Reaſon deſerve juſt as much as Spies and Plotters, if not worſe, a treble Retribution I mean, as Rogues by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple are dyed of the deepeſt grain.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That beyond this, that to hinder Men from exerciſing their particular Religions, is either by a neceſſity to promote Irreligion, or if after, you force them to the Religion of the State, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs weaker Conſciences, and make Hypocrites of them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, therefore that on theſe terms, as the Jews of old did, if our Peace be not endangered, Children are not ſacrificed, nor Beaſts in time of Famine, even the very Heathens, much more Jews, Turks, and our Brother Chriſtians of all ſorts ought to have a full and free Enjoyment of their Liberty of Conſcience amongſt us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Et floreat qui valet.</head>
               <head type="sub">Objections that ſeem to deſerve an Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That you think this Force too little, and an Inquiſition neceſſary. Ay, a fine way indeed to ſpoil all again by another ſuch irreformable State as Popery.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But may be you'll ſay, this Force is too much; yes, yes, I know your meaning, you want an Upping-ſtock, Toleration has been always good with them that are undermoſt, though none have allowed it as you ſee when they have got uppermoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But you Object, That in theſe Circumſtances the State-Religion may yet poſſibly be undermined; ay, and in God's
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65762:36"/>Name let her, if with all theſe Advantages ſhe cannot preſerve her ſelf: 'Tis too great a Preſumption to Complement all the Prieſts in <hi>Europe</hi> with to ſay, they are infallibly in the right.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the State will fall with the Church upon it, and very right, without an exchange upon it in time it might; but on the contrary, in an exchange of Religions for the better, all States whatever in the end muſt needs thrive by it.</p>
               <p>To conclude, that which bewilders Men in this caſe, is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Religion of the State may poſſibly err, and that it will be hard to have it ſet up. And truly when Men can find a Church that does not, the Objection may be formidable, in the mean while, if we are bound to bear with the Infirmities and hearty Endeavours of one another, ſurely we may be full as Charitable with the State alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the true Religion has no particular Proviſion made for it here; right, and until we can convince all the World in particular what it is, we need not fear, with the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, thus to be ſo juſt as to let our Faith fight it out fairly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt by the plain dint of Truth and Holineſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That many Conſcientious Men may ſuffer hereby: But alas, that will no more be helped by a Lawleſs Toleration, that will debauch all Religion, and ruin all Government, than a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Eſtabliſhment; there always was and will be a War on Earth between the Servants of God and the Devil, and he is an <hi>Uto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> Romancer that expects Peace till he is in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole, the Claws of Antichriſt will hereby be clip'd, the Doctrines of Peace will no longer be propagated by Blood, but Tender Conſciences will have an agreeable eaſe; and as every Church will be left to the modeſt dint of Argument, ſo the true Religion, be it where or what it will, will have all the Encouragement to be had with the Peace and Safety of the State, and more I preſume ſhe never wiſhed.</p>
               <p>I ſhall end all with a Jewiſh Story, related by Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> at the end of his Liberty of Prophecy: 'tis this, <hi>Abraham</hi> waiting at his Tent Door, as his Cuſtom was, in expectation to Entertain ſome Strangers, invites amongſt the reſt an Old Man to come in to him, but afterwards when he came to Supper, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the Old Man prayed to the Fire for his God, what does <hi>Abraham</hi> do, but as zealouſly turns him out of Doors again. But what think you follows upon it? God calls to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Night, and asks him, what he had done with the Old Man
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65762:37"/>that he had ſent him for his Gueſt? <hi>Abraham</hi> indeed relates the truth of the Fact upon it; but what ſays God to him for it? <hi>What, have I born with him from his very Youth up to theſe Years, and couldst not thou bear with him one Night?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go thou and do ſo likewiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>OF CATHOLICK COMMUNION, OR, THE <hi>Neglected Duty of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Publick Worſhip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE former Diſcourſe having not only ſhewn how Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Religion is to a State, but how Neceſſary its Union is alſo, the intent of the preſent is to demonſtrate, that as the End cannot be without the Means, ſo that even every Private Man, as well as every State, is as much engaged to a Unity in the Publick Worſhip, as to Religion it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Obligation to this Unity indeed, to the Publick and the Private Man is different; the one from Peace, and the other from Conſcience, but ſurely both alike are ſacred, and to both alike 'twould deſtroy all the good Effects and Benefits to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from Religion, inſtead of being inflam'd to Love and Peace by it, to have our Paſſions and Frailties only ting'd with the unhappy Zeal of Diſcord, to thoſe miſerable and deſperate Effects that otherwiſe even Humanity would prevent.</p>
               <p>Beſides, in Publick Unity and Love, I may ſay, God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is an Honour to him, but in endleſs Diviſions and Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, a Contumely and a Reproach rather: What, can the God of Peace and Truth be delighted in perpetual Quarrels and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riances? Or do we not rather Blaſpheme his Nature, when we think to pleaſe him with ſuch Corruptions? And even ſo in the State alſo, Religion in Unity will aſſuredly prove the ſtrongeſt Band of Concord, but in Sects and Schiſms it has no other Fruit than perverſe Wranglings and Deſtruction.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:65762:37"/>
               <p>But add to theſe the Chriſtian Obligations to a Publick Communion alſo, and then let us ſee how the matter ſtands. And thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt gave us but one new Commandment, to wit, <hi>That we love one another;</hi> and ſurely we are likely to be hopeful Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to him upon't, when we can't ſo much as agree to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Catholick Church, and the Communion of Saints, are even two of the Articles of the Apoſtles Creed; and can that Publick Unity in Worſhip be inconſiderable then, that was thought worthy even of being ſo doubly ranged in ſo conſtant and ſolemn a Profeſſion?</p>
               <p n="3">3. That 'tis not only the expreſs Promiſe of Chriſt, <hi>That where two or three are gathered together in his Name, that he is in the midst of them,</hi> to give a more particular Bleſſing to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of our ſelves, but St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and otherwhere, orders even a <hi>Cain</hi>'s Mark to be laid on thoſe that cauſe Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and omit to Aſſemble themſelves with the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17, 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10, 11. &amp; <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That we may very well diſcern what our Sentence is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be for ſuch Schiſms and Diviſions, by the Treatment of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and our Saviour himſelf's calling the <hi>Samaritans</hi> Dogs, only for their Schiſm from the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and which I am ſure did not want Errors enough.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That 'tis one of the Propheſies of the Churches Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that hereafter Men ſhould cry thus, <hi>Lo here Chriſt, and lo there; and have itching Ears after Separations, and variety and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of Teachers.</hi> And ſhould it not ſhame us then to ſtick at ſome trifling Puritan Knot, while we ſwallow a Camel in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, to the ſcandal of Chriſtianity, and the ſcoffing of Jews, Turks, and Heathens?</p>
               <p n="6">6. And laſtly, <hi>Euſebius, Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 44. tells us, that 'tis not a leſs Martyrdom rather to bear Evils, than to diſ-member the Church, than to dye for not Sacrificing to Idols. And I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> has this very Expreſſion of ſome that were <hi>Socinians</hi> in his time, in his Diſcourſe with <hi>Tryphon,</hi> p. 207. For there are ſome Dr. Friends, ſaid I, of our kind, who confeſs him to be the Chriſt, and yet hold him to be a Man born of Men. But pray, where is that Charity now, ſo to call a <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Dr. Friend, and of our kind?</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:65762:38"/>
               <p>But the better to proceed in this matter, I ſhall range my following Diſcourſe under theſe Five Heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. <hi>In ſhewing the Methods proper for ſuch a Unity.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>In ſhewing the Duty of the State towards it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>In refuting Modern Pleas for Diviſions.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>In propoſing an Accommodation between them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. <hi>In Anſwering Difficulties remaining.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>General Methods to Unity in Publick Worſhip.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That in States Siſter-Churches ought as near as poſſible to walk hand in hand with each other, whilſt all Private Men, according to the Example of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Conſcientiouſly conform to the preſent Church they are under, be it where or what it will; indeed otherwiſe to expect the End without the Means is as endleſs as impertinent, and if trifling Variances and Errors may cauſe Schiſms and Diviſions with us, we have no means left to be at Unity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As in Building a material Houſe, we are forced to hew Stones to the Wall; ſo in the immaterial Temple of God's Church alſo, how can we expect any Structure to be made if there be not a mutual bearing between the fallibility of our own Judgments and the Church, but eſpecially where the Church profeſſes her ſelf fallible.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That this bearing with Errors and Variances therefore in Churches extends to all manner of Faults whatever, provided the Church be Chriſtian, and not Idolatrous; in truth all faults elſe, whether great by number or aggravation, are alike to be born with, or elſe Church-Community muſt and ever will be but a Chymera; for what Church is, ever was, or will be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Errors in variety? And what Age has wanted wicked Men enough to aggravate them to Diviſions, if the World be not wiſer than to follow them?</p>
               <p n="4">4. That though this Charity may look like a Cowardly trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, eſpecially in ſuch a Factious Age as this, when there are almoſt as many Churches as Men, yet undoubtedly whoever will look on Church-Unity as a Practical Duty, and embrace it as ſuch, with other Reaſons than meer Partying, muſt do it on theſe grounds, or none; I am ſure by the ſame Reaſons we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Church now, we may divide it infinitely, and 'tis
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65762:38"/>almoſt a wonder there is any Communion at all left amongſt us.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly, but that nothing herein excuſe Men in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelves with Perſonal Teſts, wherein we ought to dye, rather than deny the leaſt Truth, and that though in Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the beſt of Churches. And ſurely in this caſe the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is clear enough, an <hi>Algier</hi>'s Slavery in Religion is what cannot but offend every good Man; but a mutual bearing of Evils and Errors irremediable in Publick Communions, certainly is a Duty and Charity neceſſary, or nothing in Chriſtiany is to be minded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Duty of the State towards Catholick Communion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That as the State knows that God did not give Man his Reaſon only to be wilfully blind with it, or his Eyes, to put them out to ſee, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would ſeem to ſay, by ordering an Obedience of ſetting Trees with their Roots upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, if commanded. So it is the particular Duty of the State, as to be ſuppoſed wiſer than their Subjects, rather to let the Waves of Opinions have their full Channel in their largely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Arms of Charity, like the <hi>Sadduces</hi> and <hi>Phariſee</hi> of Old in the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> than by becoming of any particular Party, to drive away all the Oppoſites from her.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And thus, what though a Man believes Tranſubſtantiation or Purgatory? They are abſurd Doctrines with hard Names it may be; but are we ſure that even we our ſelves don't hold O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions full as fooliſh of another kind, though not nick-nam'd? So, what though a Man's a <hi>Socinian?</hi> Cannot an Arch-Biſhop hear a <hi>Socinian,</hi> and a Trinitarian diſpute, as well as an High-Prieſt could a <hi>Sadducee</hi> and <hi>Phariſee</hi> of Old? Or what, may'nt I Worſhip with a <hi>Socinian,</hi> that at leaſt makes Chriſt the greateſt Prophet? When both Chriſt and his Apoſtles after him, could Worſhip even with thoſe very Jews that decryed him as an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that on this Account alſo all thoſe unaccountable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and Niceties, and fondneſs of Words, that have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto corrupted Chriſtianity ſo far from its Primitive Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, as to make it even too ſine and burthenſom, either for our Wit, Memory, or Underſtanding, whether they be true or falſe, be all equally laid aſide, without we have a mind by our Canting
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65762:39"/>
                  <hi>Jure Divino's,</hi> and Infallibility in new-coin'd Doctrines, never to let the World have Peace for us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, Therefore ſince Innovators in no Authority are to be regarded, and as it is both the particular Command and Example of Chriſt in ſuch caſes, rather to fear God than Man; ſo every State ſhould rather ſtudy to become a tender bearing Father, and a Nurſing Mother in the Church to eaſe feeble Minds, than if poſſible to hazard their Ruines, be it but with the appearance of dangerous Teſts and Offences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Modern Pleas for Schiſms anſwered.</head>
               <p n="1">1. You ſay, that <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14. makes you angry at Holy days; I pray if it does, do not keep them then, no more than Chriſt obſerved <hi>Corban</hi> with the <hi>Jews:</hi> But muſt that make you leave the Church for Sundays therefore, when the <hi>Corban</hi> could not make him leave the Temple?</p>
               <p n="2">2. You ſay, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10. makes you angry at Surplices too; and why not at formal Bands, and ſingular Cloaks as well? Nay, <hi>Socrates Schol. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 20. tells us of ſome that were angry that the Miniſters wore black, ſince Chriſt himſelf wore white. But bleſs me! if the Church may'nt be left Maſter of all ſuch Indifferencies for Decency, we may agree when we can. So,</p>
               <p n="3">3. You think that Godfathers too commonly take an Idle Oath in Baptiſm; and what then? The Oath is good in it ſelf, and was of uſe under the Primitive Perſecutions; and at preſent, is any obliged to be Goſſip againſt his will?</p>
               <p n="4">4. But you are offended at Prayer by Form you ſay: Bleſs me, that Men can be ſo ſick of Whimſies! if a Man Prays <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore,</hi> 'tis at leaſt a Form to the Congregation; it ſeems then that 'tis the Prieſt only that muſt have none, for the People muſt have one all one, and too often none of the beſt neither. So,</p>
               <p n="5">5. You have the Spirit you ſay, and more Truth than others, and you are the fitter Member in the Catholick Church to ſhew your Zeal in mending it then; what, did the Prophets of Old go to ſet up other Churches, and make Partyings, only through their being holier than other Men? No, we don't hear ſo much as of one Sect that they made; indeed they were for Correcting the Old, not confounding us with New Foundations.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:65762:39"/>6. The Quaker alſo is angry at our gayety and vanity in fine Cloaths; ay, and ſo was <hi>Iſaya</hi> with the <hi>Jews</hi> of Old too; but would <hi>Iſaya</hi> therefore ran out of the Church for it? Pray God, I ſay, their Spirit prove as good as his, I am ſure it does not ſeem ſo by this and their late Quarrels of Chriſt within, and Chriſt without.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But you would have Presbyters inſtead of Biſhops you ſay: Bleſs me, that Men ſhould quarrel about words ſo! 'tis plain, the Presbyters would be as great as the Biſhops if they could, and both alike are Scripture Names of Offices, and which many Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Men have thought to ſignifie the ſame thing. The caſe then is, we can never agree to what the Scripture-Order of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is, nor will we conſent that the State ſhould modeſtly decide the Doubt between us.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, but your Offences are not regarded, and therefore too you are further offended. Bleſs me, that Men can Argue thus! What, we have a Controverſie about Biſhops, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority it ſeems are for them; and pray, what muſt the State in this caſe do, have no Diſcipline for fear of offending your two Scruples, or let the Offence fall on the leaſt in Number? I ſay, to this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> No Diſcipline, and no Church; and therefore 'tis but as of Neceſſity that things ſhould be as they are.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Our Natural Concluſions of Accommodation are,</head>
               <p n="1">1. That though all theſe pretences are groundleſs of a right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Separation from the State-Religion; yet that the State not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding upon it is but juſt in removing thoſe things that are ill among them, as well as the others are unjuſt to them in their needleſs Schiſm for trifles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That accordingly our Pageantly Churches, too big to be heard in, our Croſs in Baptiſm, our Orthodoxy in Ceremonies only may be very well laid aſide; for though when Men are offended at us for good, we need not mind it, but rather in pity, with Chriſt, ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is he that is not offended in me.</hi> Yet when Men are offended at Indifferencies, and as the Apoſtle inſtances, in Meats offered to Idols, then by no means may we Lawfully continue to keep up their Offence. Nay,</p>
               <p n="3">3. That as we ſee by the Shew Bread that was eaten by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and his Men, and Chriſt's Licenſe to help out our Ox on the Sabbath day, that the more formal parts, even of Piety it ſelf,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65762:40"/>are to give place, where the more Eſſential or Neceſſary require; ſo ſometimes even more than indifferent may be yielded, rather than come to Blood or Diviſions: And thus you Baptize your Infant, or you eat the Lord's Body; but cannot you let another forbear therefore, as the Learned Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> has it in his Liberty of Prophecy, rather than make him defile his Conſcience?</p>
               <p n="4">4. So <hi>Euſebius, Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. tells us, that in his time it was held, that Lay-men might ſpeak in Churches; and that though even before Biſhops, purſuant to <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.4, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.46.—4.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.14.—17.22. and other Texts, ſhewing how that in that the Chriſtians purſued the Jewiſh Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; and why not to be allowed now too as well, if a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation generally conſent?</p>
               <p n="5">5. So ſome are for Praying ſtanding you ſay; and why not, ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> did but the ſame before? 'Twere decent indeed to have all kneel, but is not Unity more than Ceremony? So ſome are ignorant, you ſay; and what then? Did not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles own ſome for Diſciples, though they never heard even of the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <p n="6">6. That accordingly herein Miniſters and Congregations of all ſorts be left to their diſcretions; nay, and further, that in and about the City of <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere, where the paucity of Churches may be of further Offence, that there be full Liberty given for the further Building of Churches, to be erected and ruled, as Congregations and Paſtors ſhall by mutual conſent agree.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And that farther, as well in ſuch as all other Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to avoid all manner of Offence, the Miniſter, with the conſent of his Congregation, be allowed to Pray either by Form or <hi>Extempore,</hi> as ſhall be ſeen moſt convenient, or to uſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies or not, as they ſhall agree to let them alone.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, a Comprehenſion in a Church like this, muſt not only needs cut off all grounds of Hereſie in becoming ſo ſimply Apoſtolick, but withal force all Foreign Churches to joyn with her, and cut off all manner of colour and Foundation for Schiſms and Diviſions, I may ſay, all the miſchiefs of a Factioning To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration will be loſt in this: And as the conſiderableſt Heads of all Sects cannot but be contented with ſo innocent a State, ſo I doubt not but that all the little ſcrupuloſity which has ſo long confounded our Reformation; will in a very ſhort time be ſwallowed up by it; and as by Natural conſequence a real
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65762:40"/>Schiſmatick and Heretick will become as odious to all by one conſent as he was to the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>That which has bewildred Men here, has been,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Men ſhould be ſo heedleſs in their Diviſions as they are, to break Communion for every Trifle as they have done; but as to that I can only ſay, when Men had once treſpaſſed the true Bounds of their Duty in the Publick Unity in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, afterwards 'tis no wonder to ſee a whole Sea and Deluge of Sects and Schiſms break in upon them; for how can they hold together, that have not the leaſt Principle of Unity left, and that are linked with no other Chain than meer Faction and Party, at beſt a few criterion Tenets.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Grandeur of the Church will fall by it; and why ſo? wherein is its Grandeur but its Unity? But if you call your External Ornaments of Churches and Service, as in Cathedrals and Chappels, your Grandeur, why, can you ſay, it will be gone then more than now? A poor Church has no Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſters, no Lecturers, no Organs, no Altars, nay, and too often through a too hard impropriation, no Service neither; and why then ſhould the want of a little of this Grandeur be ſo intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the greateſt Charity to weaker Brethren, that a little ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and our own corruption can ſo eaſily diſpenſe with?</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the allowance of ſuch Practices will become a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the State; ay, and a very good one too, for none can think any ill on't; we ſhall be united and firm at home, and our love and condeſcention praiſed abroad; and ſurely that we bear with Tender Conſciences on no other terms but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and Apoſtolick Liberty and Practice, cannot have the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Scandal in it, when by it we but aim to aboliſh that real Scandal that is cauſed by our preſent Schiſms and Diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That 'tis hard, ſince the State is bound ſo far in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be obeyed by her Subjects about Religion, that yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, where even they are to blame, ſhe ſhould ſtoop lower to them; and truly if the State were not our Father as well as our Maſter, I ſhould ſay ſo too; but a Father by his Office bears with his Children, and has Patience with them; and therefore no wonder if I ſay, that ſince other meaſures have ſucceeded ſo ill, it ſhould become a State even to ſtoop a little lower alſo, and to ſee, if poſſible, the utmoſt Lenity and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can make them ſick of their Factions; and eſpecially ſince
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65762:41"/>he cannot but perceive that his fooliſh Children cannot bear other meaſures, and what he has ſo long deſigned in vain for them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That our Sectariſts will never ſatisfie themſelves, forſooth, about Epiſcopacy, Ordination, Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe they do not find nice and particular Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in Scripture about them; fear not, Time and Patience will do much, when the Prejudice of Separation is once off from them, then the Argument, that the Church was eſtabliſhed by word of Mouth, and corrected only occaſionally by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in Writing, will be enough to perſwade any reaſonable Man I am ſure, that they may juſtly let the conſent of Churches fix thoſe things in a diſcreet Order for the Glory of God, that the Holy Ghoſt for our Tryals thought not good to leave us a greater certainty in on neither ſide.</p>
               <p>To conclude, God only knows how long his Temple will be trodden under foot thus through our unhappy Morrice-dance of Sects, but be it longer or ſhorter, this I am perſwaded, when his time comes, like a Tide turned I believe he will move us as all at once to Unity, and then I know ſuch a condeſcention as this will be admired; I know at firſt a begrudging Elder Brother may diſdain thus to receive his Younger Brother in Raggs, but ſurely for all that, a true Chriſtian Father will rather kill the fatted Calf, and kiſs and embrace the poor Prodigal for joy of his Return, than begrudge him a Reception.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Glory be to God on High, on Earth Peace and Good-will towards Men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>THou ſeeſt now, Reader, that I have finiſhed as well Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix as Treatiſe, the Treatiſe to lead every Man in his Private Capacity in Religion, and the Appendix, to ſhew all Men what their Relation to the Publick Church is, and both to bring thee to that Kingdom of God that has been too long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, as well by Chriſtians as Jews, to be of this World on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: What remains then, but that I give thee two or three Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the whole, and conclude.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:65762:41"/>
               <p>The firſt is, that now thou haſt read over this Treatiſe, and while it is freſh in thy memory, I would deſire thee once more to peruſe the Scriptures after it, and to examine them, and ſee how agreeable their main purport is to it; if thou art not a <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducee,</hi> to laugh at an inviſible ſtate, or a negligent <hi>Gallio,</hi> that careth for none of theſe things, I am perſwaded thou wilt be even amazed to ſee as well how harmonious and conſonant this Treatiſe is to them, as to obſerve how ſtrangely and widely the World have hitherto miſtaken their true intent and purport.</p>
               <p>The Second Reflection is, to think what a wonderful Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gratitude and Thanks thou art indebted to thy Maker in, as well in his giving thee a Talent of Life in Proſpect of theſe Glories through his Son, as in his prolonging it, as he has daily continued to do, to the great encouragement of thy advance therein. Good God! what is Man, that thou art mindful of him, or the Son of Man, that thou ſhouldeſt not only give him Being, but thus continually attend him with the Sacred Aſſiſtances of thy Spirit, to bring him at laſt to the enjoyment of thy own Glory.</p>
               <p>My laſt Reflection is, that thou make a true uſe of theſe things; I pretend to no other Gift of Prophecy here than plain Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but thus much I dare be bold to foretel by it, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther private Man or Church make their approaches to God, they ſhall never be accepted by other ſteps than theſe: Nay, and more, I'le dare ſay, let God have given us never ſo great Promiſes, or Encouragements for the ſake of his Church, we ſhall never be the Men to receive them, nor enjoy the leaſt benefit by them, unleſs thus with an exact and humble Obedience we make our Application according to his Will.</p>
               <p>Chriſt tells us, <hi>That if our Righteouſneſs exceed not that of the Scribes and Phariſees, we ſhall never be able to enter the Kingdom of God.</hi> And give me leave to acquaint you, without Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or entring the Liſts with their Merits, we muſt have a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and a Piety, yea, and a Sincerity, and Self-denyal as great and ſingular as the Glories of that Kingdom we ſeek for, if ever we expect to reach it. Our Saviour tells us, <hi>That every Plant that his Heavenly Father hath not ſet, ſhall be rooted out:</hi> And I muſt tell you, this alone is what is his Husbandry, and no wonder therefore that our other Methods have hitherto ſucceeded ſo ill, and will yet ſucceed worſe, if we do not thus ſet about us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:42"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF the Kingdom of God in general.</hi> Pag 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Criſis of our Tryal in general.</hi> 5</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of our Evil Criſis.</hi> 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of God's Impartiality.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of our Gradual Acceſs herein.</hi> 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humility.</hi> 13</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Compleat Faith.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Objections about it.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Miracles.</hi> 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Dreams and Viſions.</hi> 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Enthuſiaſm.</hi> 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Scripture.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The State of Prophecy.</hi> 31</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Prophetick Churches.</hi> 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Objections Hiſtorical.</hi> 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Heaven.</hi> 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Preparing our ſelves.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Grace.</hi> 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Prayer.</hi> 51</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>An APPENDIX.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Perſecution.</hi> 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Catholick Communion.</hi> 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion.</hi> 74</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65762:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
